<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;काशीकरः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;काशीकरः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/1/</guid>
      <description>નવા વોનીબોએ बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् फल न कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल लघुसार राबूनाराम निशास्त्र कलालशास्त्र कल व कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल सानूशास्त्र कलामूलमात्र निशास्त्र कलानुलशास्त्र का त्र कलामलशास्त्र कलाग लामून्दशा VOLUME गुलशास्त्र INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS The Baudhayana Śrautasûtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sutra-text. The Baudhayana Śrautasutra belongs to the Krsna Yajurveda Taittiriya recension.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/2/</guid>
      <description>मामूल‍ कलामूलर लशा बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् कल त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामल THE BAUDHAYANA SRAUTASUTRA VOLUME-II लशास्त्र कलामलशास्त्र क त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र लशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कल त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल नामूलशास्त्र मूलशास्त्र INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS The Baudhayana Śrautasūtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sutra-text. The Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra belongs to the Kṛṣṇa Yajurveda Taittiriya recension.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/3/</guid>
      <description>लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र मूलशा बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् कल त्र कलामूलात्र कलामूल‍ THE BAUDHAYANA SRAUTASUTRA लशास्त्र कलामलशास्त्र कल VOLUME-III त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामुल‍ लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र मूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कल त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूलश लामूलशास्त्र भारत मूलशास्त्र लशास्त्र कल INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS The Baudhayana Śrautasūtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sutra-text. The Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra belongs to the Kṛṣṇa Yajurveda Taittirïya recension.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/4/</guid>
      <description>लामूलशास्त्र मूलशा बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् कल THE कला BAUDHAYANA SRAUTASUTRA मूलशास्त्र कलालशास्त्र कल त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल‍ लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र मूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कल कलामलशास्त्र लामूलशास्त्रमलशास्त्र ए लणार कार कल INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS The Baudhayana Śrautasūtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sutra-text. The Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra belongs to the Kṛṣṇa Yajurveda Taittirïya recension.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
