<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;काशीकरः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;काशीकरः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;નવા વોનીબોએ&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् फल न कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल लघुसार राबूनाराम निशास्त्र कलालशास्त्र कल व कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल सानूशास्त्र कलामूलमात्र निशास्त्र कलानुलशास्त्र का त्र कलामलशास्त्र कलाग&#xA;लामून्दशा&#xA;VOLUME&#xA;गुलशास्त्र&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS&#xA;The Baudhayana Śrautasûtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sutra-text. The Baudhayana Śrautasutra belongs to the Krsna Yajurveda Taittiriya recension. It represents the oral lectures delivered by the teacher Baudhāyana, hence is the oldest śrauta-text. The text is revised here in the light of the variant readings recorded by W. Caland in his first edition (Calcutta 1906), and is presented in a readable form. The mantras forming part of the sutras have been fully rendered into English. The translation is supplied with notes giving reference to the mantras and explanations of the ritual. The work is expected to serve as an advancement of Taittiriya ritualistic studies.&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE BAUDHAYANA ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;कलामूलशास्त्र-ग्रन्थमाला KALĀMŪLAŠĀSTRA SERIES&#xA;इ.गा.रा.क. के. क. मू.शा - ३५ I.G.N.C.A. K.M.S. - 35&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE BAUDHAYANA ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;CRITICALLY EDITED AND TRANSLATED&#xA;BY&#xA;C.G. KASHIKAR&#xA;VOLUME ONE&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS NEW DELHI AND&#xA;MOTILAL BANARSIDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD.&#xA;DELHI&#xA;First Published: 2003&#xA;Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Arts&#xA;All rights reserved. No part of the publication may be reproduced in any form or by any means, without written permission of the publishers.&#xA;Published by&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS Central Vista Mess, Janpath, New Delhi-110001&#xA;in association with&#xA;MOTILAL BANARSIDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD. Bungalow Road, Jawahar Nagar, Delhi 110 007&#xA;ISBN: 81-208-1853-9 (Vol. I) ISBN: 81-208-1852-0 (Set) Price: Rs. 4200.00 (Set)&#xA;Typeset by Neographics K-2071 (1st Floor), Chittaranjan Park, New Delhi-110019 Printed in India&#xA;at Shri Jainendra Press,&#xA;A-45, Naraina Industrial Area, Phase-I,&#xA;New Delhi-110 028&#xA;PREFACE&#xA;I am extermely happy to present to the world of scholars the text of the Baudhāyana Śrautasutra together with an English translation and notes. The first critical edition of this Śrautasūtra was prepared by W. Caland and was published in three volumes by the Asiatic Society of Bengal, Calcutta (1904-13). Its second edition-a reprint-was published at New Delhi in 1982. My translation is of course based on Caland&amp;rsquo;s edition. A faithful translation of any ancient text, particularly a Vedic text, involves a thorough understanding of the text. Consequently I have paid close attention to the rich treasure of variant readings recorded by Caland in his Foot- notes. As a result of my close study of the text in all aspects and the numerous variant readings, I have improved the text at numerous places. Sometimes I have had to resort to emendation of certain readings. In my notes to the translation I have noted all such places where I have chosen a reading different from that of Caland&amp;rsquo;s printed text. The text printed herein is thus, the Baudhāyana Śrautasûtra text in a revised form. I have excluded the Śulbasūtra (Praśna XXX) and the Pravarapraśna for reasons mentioned in the Introduction.&#xA;A new critical edition of the Baudhayana Śrautasūtra needs to be undertaken. Caland had utilised a number of manuscripts of the text for his edition. He has, however, left numerous doubtful places, particularly in Praśnas X-XIX. The Mackenzie Collection manuscript No. xxviii (new number 92), a Descriptive Cata- logue of the Oriental MSS collected by Lt. Col. Mackenzieedited by H.H. Wilson Vol. I. p.6 rendered him valuable help in defining the text and also the order of the text. Numerous textual difficulties still exist, and these require to be solved. Many more manuscripts of the Baudhayana Śrautasutra which were not available to Caland have fortunately been discovered and stored in manuscript-libraries. These manuscripts are indeed a great treasure which needs to be exploited. One may perhaps find among them manuscripts representing the tradition of Mackenzie manuscripts or even a better preserved tradition. The study of Śrautasūtras is far advanced since Caland published his edition. Consequently a new critical edition undertaken by an expert brain will be welcome. Since the text presented herein is only a revision of Caland&amp;rsquo;s text, I have not found it necessary to reproduce the variant readings recorded by Caland in his Footnotes.&#xA;The Vedic texts by their very nature were not fully comprehensible by themselves to a student of literature and religion. Hence, the various means like the Bhāṣyas, Tīkās, Paddhatis and Prayogas came to be produced from time to time. The old commentators among them were rather brief because in their view only a few hints were sufficient for the elucidation of the text in hand. The later&#xA;vi&#xA;BAUDHAYANAŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;commentators, on the other hand, wrote in rather a liberal manner because they thought the reader of their time was in need of detailed explanations. In modern times when modern dialects have become the vehicle of all communication and when visions of understanding have considerably widened, it became imperative to explain all old texts, particularly the Vedic, through translation and notes in modern languages.&#xA;Many of the Kalpasūtras have been translated into English, German, Dutch, French and other languages. The Baudhāyana Śrautasutra holds a prominent position among the Kalpasūtras for various reasons. It is extensive and dilates upon the sacrificial religion in a comprehensive manner. Full understanding of this text is essential for the scientific knowledge of the Vedic religion and culture. No complete translation of this significant text has been attempted so far in any language. Some portions of it have been rendered into English in detached manner in the various parts of the Śrautakosa published by the Vaidika Samshodhana&#xA;Mandala at Pune. Herein the mantras have not been translated. Yasuke Ikari has translated in English the tenth chapter of this text laying down the piling up of the Fire-altar (Agnicayana) in the Volume of Agni (Berkley, 1983) again without the translation of the mantras.&#xA;A complete English translation of the Baudhāyana Śrautasutra was therefore a desideratum, and it is my privilege to fill in the gap. In my translation I have mostly translated the mantra side by side with the injunctive part of a sutra. The Taittirīya- texts comprise both the mantra-portions and the Brāhmaṇa-portions. There is definite correlation between the mantra and the Brahmana. One cannot be fully understood without the other. This is true of the prose formulas and also of the verses. Such verses as are common to the Rgveda may bear loose relation to the ritual. I have not translated the Puronuvākyā and Yājyā verses which may hardly be said to have close relation to the ritual. While translating a mantra I have kept in view the relation of the mantra to the corresponding Brāhmaṇa. In this behalf I have consulted the commentaries by Bhatta Bhaskara and Sāyaṇa on the Taittiriya texts, who I believe, even though remote in time from the Taittiriya texts, were mostly conversant with that relation through their intimate knowledge of the continued ritual tradition. Even then I have not ignored the principles of Philology in translating the mantras.&#xA;In translating the Sūtra-text I have consulted Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s Bhāṣya and also the commentary Subodhini as far as it is available. Even then certain points have remained obscure to me. Footnotes are added to the translation. References to the original sources of the mantra and Brahmana passages are given in the Footnotes.&#xA;The Dvaidhasutra always goes in concurrence with the main text. Caland has, in his edition of the text, tried to give the references to the main text while presenting the Dvaidhasūtra. In some cases references have not been given by him.PREFACE&#xA;vii&#xA;I have tried my best to give at such places the references to the main text. The same thing applies to the Karmantasūtra also. I have tried to make the translation as literal as possible. Words essential for clear understanding have been put in parenthesis.&#xA;Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s vivarana on a major portion of the Baudhayana Śrautasūtra is available in manuscripts. Caland had intended to edit this vivarana which is a veritable source for good understanding of Baudhāyana&amp;rsquo;s text. He however abandoned his design since the manuscript-material available to him was utterly insufficient. He has stated, &amp;ldquo;Perhaps I may in later times fulfil also this promise. (Preface to Vol. II p. xi). He however could not do so. T.N. Dharmadhikari has prepared a critical edition of the vivarana after a careful study of the available defective manuscripts. He has tried his best to present a readable text of the vivarana and has recorded the variants in Foot-notes. The vivarana is appended. A Glossary is also appended. The index of words prepared by my student Smt. Leena Sabnis will be found useful for a scientific study of the text.&#xA;I am grateful to the authorities of the Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Arts, New Delhi, for assigning the project to me. I have tried to complete it to the best of my ability. The Centre granted me all facilities for the carrying out of the project. I am glad to acknowledge the help which I have received in completing the project. Caland&amp;rsquo;s scholarly monograph Uber das rituelle Sūtra des Baudhāyana was a constant help to me. Many decades have passed since Caland published his monumental work. Knowledge of the ritualistic religion has considerably advanced during this time, and it has become possible to add to our knowledge of Baudhāyana&amp;rsquo;s text. I have also consulted Caland&amp;rsquo;s voluminous work on other Vedic texts and the scholarly work of Indian and western scholars including J.Gonda&amp;rsquo;s History of Indian Literature. I thank Kumari Saroj Deshpande for neatly preparing the typescript of&#xA;the translation.&#xA;When in 1903 he published his important monograph Über das rituelle Sūtra des Baudhayana, W. Caland concluded by saying, &amp;ldquo;Möchte es mir gelingen sein, ein Interesse für diesen Text zu wecken&amp;rdquo; (p. 65). By simultaneously publishing his important edition of the Baudhāyana Srautasūtra, he may be said to have laid the foundation not only of the all-round study of this oldest Srautasūtra but also of the Śrauta texts in general. Since then significant research work has been done in the field of the ritual Sūtras. I hope this edition of the revised text together with translation and Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s vivarana will give a new impetus to the study of the Vedic ritualistic religion.&#xA;Pune, October 2, 2001&#xA;Gandhi Jayanti&#xA;C.G. KASHIKAR&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;Preface Introduction&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;मामूल‍&#xA;कलामूलर&#xA;लशा बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् कल&#xA;त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामल&#xA;THE&#xA;BAUDHAYANA SRAUTASUTRA&#xA;VOLUME-II&#xA;लशास्त्र कलामलशास्त्र क त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र लशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कल त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल&#xA;नामूलशास्त्र&#xA;मूलशास्त्र&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS&#xA;The Baudhayana Śrautasūtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sutra-text. The&#xA;Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra belongs to the Kṛṣṇa Yajurveda Taittiriya recension. It represents the oral lectures delivered by the teacher Baudhāyana, hence is the oldest śrauta-text. The text is revised here in the light of the variant readings recorded by W. Caland in his first edition (Calcutta 1906), and is presented in a readable form. The mantras forming part of the sutras have been fully rendered into English. The translation is supplied with notes giving reference to the mantras and explanations of the ritual. The work is expected to serve as an advancement of Taittiriya ritualistic studies.&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE BAUDHAYANA ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;कलामूलशास्त्र-ग्रन्थमाला KALĀMŪLAŠĀSTRA SERIES&#xA;इ.गा.रा.क.के.क.मू.शा - ३६&#xA;I.G.N.C.A. K.M.S. - 36&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE BAUDHAYANA ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;CRITICALLY EDITED AND TRANSLATED&#xA;BY&#xA;C.G. KASHIKAR&#xA;VOLUME TWO&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS NEW DELHI AND&#xA;MOTILAL BANARSIDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD.&#xA;DELHI.&#xA;First Published: 2003&#xA;Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Arts&#xA;All rights reserved. No part of the publication may be reproduced in any form or by any means, without written permission of the publishers.&#xA;Published by&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS Central Vista Mess, Janpath, New Delhi-110001&#xA;in association with&#xA;MOTILAL BANARSIDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD. Bungalow Road, Jawahar Nagar, Delhi 110 007&#xA;ISBN: 81-208-1854-7 (Vol. II) ISBN: 81-208-1852-0 (Set) Price: Rs. 4200.00 (Set)&#xA;Typeset by Neographics K-2071 (1st Floor), Chittaranjan Park, New Delhi-110019 Printed in India&#xA;at Shri Jainendra Press,&#xA;A-45, Naraina Industrial Area, Phase-I,&#xA;New Delhi-110 028&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;PRAŚNA&#xA;PAGES&#xA;AGNIṢTOMA&#xA;VI-VIII&#xA;276-473&#xA;Morning Pressing&#xA;VII.1-20&#xA;350-413&#xA;Midday Pressing&#xA;VIII.1-8&#xA;414-437&#xA;Third Pressing&#xA;VIII.9-22&#xA;437-473&#xA;PRAVARGYA&#xA;IX.1-20&#xA;474-543&#xA;Pravargyavidhi&#xA;IX.1-16&#xA;474-525&#xA;Gharmaprayaścittāni&#xA;IX.17-18&#xA;525-537&#xA;Avāntaradīkṣā&#xA;IX.19-20&#xA;537-543&#xA;AGNICAYANA&#xA;X.1-59&#xA;544-707&#xA;VĀJAPEYA&#xA;XI.1-13&#xA;708-741&#xA;RĀJASŪYA&#xA;XII.1-20&#xA;742-787&#xA;ABBREVIATIONS&#xA;App&#xA;APSS ÁsvSS&#xA;AV&#xA;Apparently Apastamba Śrautasūtra Aśvalayana Śrautasūtra Atharvaveda Samhitā&#xA;BaudhŚS&#xA;Baudhayana Śrautasūtra&#xA;BhārŚS&#xA;DhS&#xA;GS&#xA;JAOS&#xA;JBr&#xA;JBRAS&#xA;KausBr&#xA;KathŚS&#xA;Bharadvaja Śrautasūtra Dharma Sutra&#xA;Grhya Sūtra&#xA;Journal of American Oriental Society Jaiminiya Brāhmaṇa&#xA;Journal of Bombay Royal Asiatic Society Kausitaki Brāhmaṇa&#xA;Kathaka Śrautasūtra&#xA;KatyŚS&#xA;Kātyāyana Śrautasūtra&#xA;KS&#xA;Kāthaka Samhitā&#xA;MānέS&#xA;Mānava Śrautasūtra&#xA;MS&#xA;Maitrāyaṇi Samhitā&#xA;MSS&#xA;Manuscripts&#xA;RV&#xA;ŞadBr&#xA;Śǎnkh GS&#xA;ŚBr&#xA;ŚS&#xA;ŚuS&#xA;TĀ&#xA;TāndBr&#xA;TBr&#xA;TS&#xA;Rgveda Samhitā Şaḍvimsa Brāhmaṇa&#xA;Śānkhāyana Gṛhya Sutra&#xA;Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa Śānkhāyana Sūtra Šulba Sūtra Taittiriya Aranyaka&#xA;Tandya Brāhmaṇa Taittiriya Brāhmaṇa&#xA;Taittiriya Samhitā&#xA;VādhŚS&#xA;Vādhūla Śrautasūtra&#xA;VS&#xA;VSK&#xA;Vājasaneyi Samhita&#xA;Vājasaneyi Samhitā Kāṇva&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/3/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र मूलशा बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् कल त्र कलामूलात्र कलामूल‍&#xA;THE&#xA;BAUDHAYANA SRAUTASUTRA&#xA;लशास्त्र कलामलशास्त्र कल&#xA;VOLUME-III&#xA;त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामुल‍ लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र मूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कल त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूलश&#xA;लामूलशास्त्र&#xA;भारत&#xA;मूलशास्त्र&#xA;लशास्त्र कल&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS&#xA;The Baudhayana Śrautasūtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvamin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sutra-text. The&#xA;Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra belongs to the Kṛṣṇa Yajurveda Taittirïya recension. It represents the oral lectures delivered by the teacher Baudhāyana, hence is the oldest śrauta-text. The text is revised here in the light of the variant readings recorded by W. Caland in his first edition (Calcutta 1906), and is presented in a readable form. The mantras forming part of the sutras have been fully rendered into English. The translation is supplied with notes giving reference to the mantras and explanations of the ritual. The work is expected to serve as an advancement of Taittirīya ritualistic studies.&#xA;7&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE BAUDHAYANA ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;कलामूलशास्त्र-ग्रन्थमाला KALĀMŪLAŚÄSTRA SERIES&#xA;इ.गा.रा.क. के. क. मू.शा - ३७&#xA;I.G.N.C.A. K.M.S. - 37&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE BAUDHAYANA ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;CRITICALLY EDITED AND TRANSLATED&#xA;BY&#xA;C.G. KASHIKAR&#xA;VOLUME THREE&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS NEW DELHI&#xA;AND&#xA;MOTILAL BANARSIDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD.&#xA;DELHI&#xA;First Published: 2003&#xA;Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Arts&#xA;All rights reserved. No part of the publication may be reproduced in any form or by any means, without written permission of the publishers.&#xA;Published by&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS Central Vista Mess, Janpath, New Delhi-110001&#xA;in association with&#xA;MOTILAL BANARSIDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD. Bungalow Road, Jawahar Nagar, Delhi 110 007&#xA;ISBN: 81-208-1855-5 (Vol. III) ISBN: 81-208-1852-0 (Set) Price: Rs. 4200.00 (Set)&#xA;Typeset by Neographics K-2071 (1st Floor), Chittaranjan Park, New Delhi-110019 Printed in India&#xA;at Shri Jainendra Press,&#xA;A-45, Naraina Industrial Area, Phase-I,&#xA;New Delhi-110 028&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;PRAŚNA&#xA;PAGES&#xA;ISTIKALPA&#xA;AUPANUVĀKYAM&#xA;XIII.1-43&#xA;788-849&#xA;XIV.1-30&#xA;850-939&#xA;AŠVAMEDHAḤ&#xA;XV.1-38&#xA;940-1023&#xA;DVĀDASAHAḤ&#xA;XVI.1-12&#xA;1024-1041&#xA;GAVĀM AYANAM&#xA;XVI.13-23&#xA;1040-1053&#xA;AHĪNĀḤ&#xA;XVI.24-36&#xA;1052-1071&#xA;Dviratraḥ&#xA;XVI.24-27&#xA;1052-1059&#xA;Triratraḥ&#xA;XVI.24&#xA;1052-1053&#xA;Catūrātraḥ&#xA;XVI.28&#xA;1058-1059&#xA;Pañcarātraḥ&#xA;XVI.29&#xA;1058-1061&#xA;Sarasvata Ayanam&#xA;XVI.29&#xA;1060-1061&#xA;Munyayanam&#xA;XVI.30&#xA;1060-1061&#xA;Saptarātraḥ&#xA;XVI.31&#xA;1060-1063&#xA;Aṣṭarātraḥ&#xA;XVI.31&#xA;1062-1063&#xA;Navaratraḥ&#xA;XVI.31&#xA;1062-1063&#xA;Dasarātraḥ&#xA;XVI.31&#xA;1062-1063&#xA;Ekādasarātraḥ&#xA;XVI.32&#xA;1064-1065&#xA;Jyotiryanam&#xA;XVI.32&#xA;1064-1065&#xA;Trayodasarātraḥ&#xA;XVI.32&#xA;1064-1065&#xA;Caturdaŝarātraḥ-Ekavimsatirātraḥ XVI.33&#xA;1064-1067&#xA;Caturviṁśatirātraḥ&#xA;XVI.34-35&#xA;1066-1069&#xA;Sattrimsadrātraḥ-Sahasrarātraḥ XVI.36&#xA;1068-1071&#xA;UTTARĀTATIḤ&#xA;XVII-XVIII&#xA;1072-1163&#xA;Atirātraḥ&#xA;XVII.1-10&#xA;1072-1087&#xA;Ekādaŝinī&#xA;XVII.11-16&#xA;1086-1095&#xA;Punaścitiḥ&#xA;XVII.17&#xA;1094-1097&#xA;Sarpasattram&#xA;XVII.18&#xA;1096-1099&#xA;Viśvasṛjām Sattram&#xA;XVII.19&#xA;1098-1099&#xA;Kunḍapāyinām Ayanam&#xA;XVII.20-21&#xA;1100-1103&#xA;Utsargiņām Ayanam&#xA;XVII.22&#xA;1102-1103&#xA;Tapascitām Ayanam&#xA;XVII.23&#xA;1102-1105&#xA;Aharahaścayanam&#xA;XVII.24&#xA;1104-1105&#xA;Upariṣṭānmāsam&#xA;Purastānmāsam&#xA;XVII.25&#xA;1106-1107&#xA;XVII.26&#xA;1106-1107&#xA;vi&#xA;BAUDHAYANAŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;PRAŠNA&#xA;PAGES&#xA;Brahmano&amp;rsquo;yanam&#xA;XVII.27&#xA;1108-1109&#xA;Chandaścit&#xA;XVII.28&#xA;1108-1111&#xA;Rathacakracit&#xA;XVII.29&#xA;1110-1111&#xA;Droṇacit&#xA;XVII.29&#xA;1110-1111&#xA;Samühyacit&#xA;XVII.29&#xA;1110-1111&#xA;Paricayyacit&#xA;XVII.29&#xA;1110-1111&#xA;Śmaśānacit&#xA;XVII.30&#xA;1112-1113&#xA;Sautrāmaṇī&#xA;XVII.31-38&#xA;1112-1125&#xA;Samāvartanam&#xA;XVII.39-44&#xA;1124-1135&#xA;Naistyayanam&#xA;XVII.45-46&#xA;1134-1139&#xA;Kāmyā Darŝapūrṇamāsāḥ&#xA;XVII.47-54&#xA;1138-1149&#xA;Caturmāsyāḥ Somāḥ&#xA;XVII.55-58&#xA;1148-1157&#xA;Jyotirayanam&#xA;XVII.59-60&#xA;1156-1159&#xA;Mahāyajñaḥ&#xA;XVII61-62&#xA;1158-1163&#xA;EKĀHĀḤ&#xA;Bṛhaspatisavaḥ&#xA;Sthapatisavaḥ&#xA;Sūtasavaḥ&#xA;XVIII.1-53&#xA;1164-1253&#xA;XVIII.1-2&#xA;1164-1167&#xA;XVIII.3&#xA;1166-1169&#xA;XVIII.4&#xA;1168-1169&#xA;Somasavaḥ&#xA;XVIII.5&#xA;1168-1171&#xA;Pṛthisavah&#xA;XVIII.6&#xA;1170-1173&#xA;Gosavaḥ&#xA;XVIII.7&#xA;1172-1173&#xA;Odanasavaḥ&#xA;XVIII.8-10&#xA;1172-1181&#xA;Pañcaśāradīyaḥ&#xA;XVIII.11&#xA;1180-1183&#xA;Agnistut&#xA;XVIII.12-13&#xA;1182-1187&#xA;Indrastut&#xA;XVIII.14&#xA;1188-1191&#xA;Aptoryāmaḥ&#xA;XVIII.15&#xA;1190-1193&#xA;Mṛtyusavaḥ&#xA;XVIII.16-19&#xA;1192-1201&#xA;Sadyaskrī&#xA;XVIII.20-23&#xA;1200-1207&#xA;Vratyastomāḥ&#xA;XVIII.24-26&#xA;1206-1211&#xA;Bhāllavistomāḥ&#xA;XVIII.27&#xA;1210-1211&#xA;Upahavyaḥ&#xA;XVIII.28&#xA;1212-1213&#xA;Tivrasomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.29-30&#xA;1212-1217&#xA;Vighanaḥ&#xA;XVIII.30&#xA;1214-1215&#xA;Udbhid-Valabhid&#xA;XVIII.31&#xA;1216-1217&#xA;Rtapeyah&#xA;XVIII.32-34&#xA;1218-1223&#xA;Disām Catuṣṭomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.34&#xA;1220-1221&#xA;Chandasām Ekatrika&#xA;XVIII.34&#xA;1220-1221CONTENTS&#xA;vii&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;PRAŚNA&#xA;PAGES&#xA;Stomāñam Ekatrikam&#xA;XVIII.34&#xA;1222-1223&#xA;Indrāgniyoḥ Kulāyaḥ&#xA;XVIII.35&#xA;1222-1223&#xA;Śyenaḥ&#xA;XVIII.36&#xA;1222-1225&#xA;Isuḥ&#xA;XVIII.36&#xA;1222-1223&#xA;Samdamśaḥ&#xA;XVIII.36&#xA;1224-1225&#xA;Indravajraḥ&#xA;XVIII.36&#xA;1224-1225&#xA;Duraśaḥ&#xA;XVIII.37-39&#xA;1224-1227&#xA;Durṇāśaḥ&#xA;XVIII.38&#xA;1226-1227&#xA;Apacitiḥ&#xA;XVIII.38&#xA;1226-1229&#xA;Tvisih&#xA;XVIII.39&#xA;1226-1228&#xA;Rṣabhah&#xA;XVIII.40-41&#xA;1228-1229&#xA;Vanisthusavaḥ&#xA;XVIII.40&#xA;1228-1231&#xA;Kānāndhayajñaḥ&#xA;XVIII.41&#xA;1230-1231&#xA;Manuyajñaḥ&#xA;XVIII.42&#xA;1230-1233&#xA;Vācaḥstomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.42&#xA;1232-1233&#xA;Yamastomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.43&#xA;1232-1235&#xA;Śadaupasadau&#xA;XVIII.44-45&#xA;1234-1239&#xA;Punastomaḥ (i)&#xA;XVIII.46-47&#xA;1238-1243&#xA;Punastomah (ii)&#xA;XVIII.47&#xA;1240-1243&#xA;Pranodaḥ&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1242-1243&#xA;Vibādhaḥ&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1242-1243&#xA;Pratinodaḥ&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1242-1243&#xA;Agner Ativyādhaḥ&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1242-1243&#xA;Indravajraḥ&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1242-1243&#xA;Śunaskarṇayajñaḥ&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1242-1243&#xA;Rasimarayau&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1244-1245&#xA;Añjanābhyañjanau&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1244-1245&#xA;Viṣūcīnaśālaḥ&#xA;XVIII.48&#xA;1244-1245&#xA;Sarvatomukhaḥ&#xA;XVIII.49&#xA;1244-1247&#xA;Sahasraśāla&#xA;XVIII.49&#xA;1246-1247&#xA;Yamau Stomau&#xA;XVIII.50&#xA;1246-1249&#xA;Agnyãdityayoḥ Stomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.50&#xA;1248-1249&#xA;Peyani&#xA;XVIII.51&#xA;1248-1251&#xA;Disām Stomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.52&#xA;1250-1253&#xA;Rtūnām Stomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.52&#xA;1250-1251&#xA;Rṣiņām Stomaḥ&#xA;XVIII.52&#xA;1250-1251&#xA;Devatānāṁ Stomah&#xA;XVIII.52&#xA;1252-1253&#xA;viii&#xA;BAUDHAYANAŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;PRAŚNA&#xA;PAGES&#xA;Darsapurṇamāsayor Ayanam&#xA;XVIII.53&#xA;1252-1253&#xA;KĀTHAKAM&#xA;XIX.1-10&#xA;1254-1313&#xA;Sāvitraḥ&#xA;XIX.1-5&#xA;1254-1271&#xA;Nāciketah&#xA;XIX.6&#xA;1270-1275&#xA;Brahmacit&#xA;XIX.7&#xA;1274-1283&#xA;Samastaḥ&#xA;XIX.8&#xA;1282-1283&#xA;Vaiśvasrjaḥ&#xA;XIX.9&#xA;1284-1291&#xA;Āruṇaketukaḥ&#xA;XIX.10&#xA;1290-1313&#xA;App&#xA;APSS AšvŚS&#xA;AV&#xA;BaudhŚS&#xA;BhārŚS&#xA;DhS&#xA;GS&#xA;JAOS&#xA;JBr&#xA;JBRAS&#xA;KausBr&#xA;KāthŚS&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shrautam/kAshIkaraH/4/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;लामूलशास्त्र&#xA;मूलशा बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम् कल&#xA;THE&#xA;कला&#xA;Baudhāyana SRAUTASUTRA&#xA;मूलशास्त्र कलालशास्त्र कल त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कलामूल‍ लामूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र मूलशास्त्र कलामूलशास्त्र कल&#xA;कलामलशास्त्र लामूलशास्त्रमलशास्त्र&#xA;ए&#xA;लणार कार कल&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS&#xA;The Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra together with an English translation is being presented here in four volumes. There will be other volumes also presenting Bhavasvāmin&amp;rsquo;s bhāṣya and the word-index of the sūtra-text. The&#xA;Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra belongs to the Kṛṣṇa Yajurveda Taittirïya recension. It represents the oral lectures delivered by the teacher Baudhāyana, hence is the oldest śrauta-text. The text is revised here in the light of the variant readings recorded by W. Caland in his first edition (Calcutta 1906), and is presented in a readable form. The mantras forming part of the sutras have been fully rendered into English. The translation is supplied with notes giving reference to the mantras and explanations of the ritual. The work is expected to serve as an advancement of Taittiriya ritualistic studies.&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE Baudhāyana ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;कलामूलशास्त्र-ग्रन्थमाला KALĀMŪLAŠĀSTRA SERIES&#xA;इ.गा.रा.क.के. क. मू.शा - ३८&#xA;I.G.N.C.A. K.M.S. - 38&#xA;बौधायन श्रौतसूत्रम्&#xA;THE Baudhāyana ŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;CRITICALLY EDITED AND TRANSLATED&#xA;BY&#xA;C.G. KASHIKAR&#xA;VOLUME FOUR&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS NEW DELHI AND&#xA;MOTILAL BANArsiDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD.&#xA;DELHI&#xA;First Published: 2003&#xA;Indira Gandhi National Centre for the Arts&#xA;All rights reserved. No part of the publication may be reproduced in any form or by any means, without written permission of the publishers.&#xA;Published by&#xA;INDIRA GANDHI NATIONAL CENTRE FOR THE ARTS Central Vista Mess, Janpath, New Delhi-110001&#xA;in association with&#xA;MOTILAL BANArsiDASS PUBLISHERS PVT. LTD. Bungalow Road, Jawahar Nagar, Delhi 110 007&#xA;ISBN: 81-208-1856-3 (Vol. IV) ISBN: 81-208-1852-0 (Set) Price: Rs. 4200.00 (Set)&#xA;Typeset by Neographics K-2071 (1st Floor), Chittaranjan Park, New Delhi-110019 Printed in India&#xA;at Shri Jainendra Press,&#xA;A-45, Naraina Industrial Area, Phase-I,&#xA;New Delhi-110 028&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;DVAIDHASÜTRAM&#xA;PRAŚNA&#xA;PAGES&#xA;XX-XXIII&#xA;1314-1533&#xA;Drasa-pūrṇamāsau&#xA;XX.1-15&#xA;1314-1351&#xA;Agnyādheyam&#xA;XX.16-18&#xA;1350-1359&#xA;Punarādheyam&#xA;XX.19&#xA;1360-1363&#xA;Agnihotram&#xA;XX.20&#xA;1362-1365&#xA;Pindapitṛyajñaḥ&#xA;XX.21&#xA;1364-1367&#xA;Āgrayanam&#xA;XX.22&#xA;1368-1369&#xA;Agnyupasthanam&#xA;XX.23-24&#xA;1368-1375&#xA;Paśubandhaḥ&#xA;XX.25-31&#xA;1374-1391&#xA;Căturmāsyāni&#xA;XXI.1-6&#xA;1392-1405&#xA;Agniṣṭomaḥ&#xA;XXI.7-26&#xA;1404-1449&#xA;Agnikalpam&#xA;XXII.1-12&#xA;1450-1473&#xA;Vājapeyaḥ&#xA;XXII.13-15&#xA;1472-1479&#xA;Rājasūyaḥ&#xA;XXII.16-21&#xA;1478-1487&#xA;Istikalpaḥ&#xA;XXIII.1-4&#xA;1488-1497&#xA;Aupānuvākyam&#xA;XXIII.5-8&#xA;1498-1507&#xA;Dvādaśāhaḥ&#xA;XXII.9-11&#xA;1506-1513&#xA;Samvatsarika Sattra&#xA;XXII.11&#xA;1512-1513&#xA;Ahīnāḥ&#xA;XXIII.12-13&#xA;1512-1519&#xA;Atirātrah&#xA;XXIII.13&#xA;1516-1519&#xA;Ekādašinī&#xA;XXIII.14-15&#xA;1518-1523&#xA;Punaścitiḥ&#xA;XXIII.14&#xA;1520-1521&#xA;Kauṇḍapāyinām Ayanam&#xA;XXIII.14&#xA;1520-1521&#xA;Aharahaścitih&#xA;XXIII.15&#xA;1522-1523&#xA;Rathacakracitiḥ&#xA;XXIII.15&#xA;1522-1523&#xA;Sautrāmaṇī&#xA;XXIII.16-17&#xA;1522-1527&#xA;Ayanāni&#xA;XXIII.16&#xA;1524-1525&#xA;Ekāhāḥ&#xA;XXIII.18&#xA;1526-1529&#xA;Sarvatomukham&#xA;XXIII.19&#xA;1530-1533&#xA;KARMANTASŪTRAM&#xA;XXIV-XXVI&#xA;1534-1715&#xA;Paribhāṣāḥ&#xA;XXIV.1-11&#xA;1534-1549&#xA;Agnyādheyam&#xA;XXIV.12-17&#xA;1548-1557&#xA;Punarādheyam&#xA;XXIV.18-19&#xA;1558-1561&#xA;Darsa-Pūrņmāsau&#xA;XXIV.20-29&#xA;1560-1573&#xA;Agnihotram&#xA;XXIV.30-31&#xA;1572-1577&#xA;vi&#xA;BAUDHAYANAŚRAUTASŪTRA&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;PRAŠNA&#xA;PAGES&#xA;Āgrayaṇam&#xA;Pinḍapitryajñaḥ&#xA;Agnyupasthānam&#xA;Paśubandhah&#xA;XXIV.32&#xA;1576-1579&#xA;XXIV.33&#xA;1578-1581&#xA;XXIV.33&#xA;1580-1581&#xA;XXIV.34-37&#xA;1580-1587&#xA;Kāmyāḥ Pašavaḥ&#xA;XXIV.38-39&#xA;1586-1591&#xA;Caturmāsyāni&#xA;XXV.1-3&#xA;1592-1599&#xA;Agniṣṭomaḥ&#xA;XXV.4-26&#xA;1598-1637&#xA;Agnicayanam&#xA;XXV.27-32&#xA;1636-1649&#xA;Vājapeyaḥ&#xA;XXV.33-34&#xA;1648-1653&#xA;Rājasūyaḥ&#xA;XXVI. 1-3&#xA;1654-1659&#xA;Istikalpaḥ&#xA;XXVI.4-6&#xA;1658-1667&#xA;Aupānuvākyam&#xA;XXVI.7-9&#xA;1666-1671&#xA;Aśvamedhaḥ&#xA;XXVI. 10-11&#xA;1670-1677&#xA;Dvādasahaḥ&#xA;XXVI.12-17&#xA;1676-1685&#xA;Ahīnāḥ&#xA;XXVI.18-21&#xA;1684-1691&#xA;Atirātraḥ&#xA;XXVI.22&#xA;1690-1693&#xA;Sautrāmaṇī&#xA;XXVI.22&#xA;1692-1693&#xA;Ekādaśinī&#xA;XXVI.23-24&#xA;1692-1697&#xA;Sarpāņām Ayanam&#xA;XXVI.24&#xA;1696-1697&#xA;Viśvasrjām Ayanam&#xA;XXVI.24&#xA;1696-1697&#xA;Kundapāyinām Ayanam etc.&#xA;XXVI.25&#xA;1696-1699&#xA;Utsargiņām Ayanam&#xA;XXVI.26&#xA;1698-1701&#xA;Tapaścitām Ayanam&#xA;Aharahaścayanam&#xA;XXVI.27&#xA;1700-1703&#xA;Uparisṭānmāsam&#xA;Purastānmāsam&#xA;Brahmano&amp;rsquo;yanam Kāmyāścitayaḥ Ekāhāh&#xA;PRĀYAŚCITTASŪTRAM&#xA;XXVI.28-29&#xA;1702-1705&#xA;XXVI.30-33&#xA;1706-1715&#xA;XXVII-XXIX&#xA;1716-1807&#xA;Istiprāyaścittāni&#xA;XXVII.1-13&#xA;1716-1741&#xA;Hutanumantraṇāni&#xA;XXVII.14&#xA;1740-1743&#xA;Mrgarestiḥ&#xA;XXVIII.1&#xA;1744-1747&#xA;Pavitreştiḥ&#xA;XXVIII.2&#xA;1746-1755&#xA;Nakṣatreṣṭayaḥ&#xA;XXVIII.3-4&#xA;1754-1761&#xA;Agrayaṇestiprāyaścittam&#xA;XXVIII.5&#xA;1760-1761&#xA;Paśuprāyaścittāni&#xA;XXVIII.6-7&#xA;1760-1765&#xA;Caturmasyaprayaścittāni&#xA;XXVIII.8&#xA;1764-1767&#xA;TOPIC&#xA;Adhvaradikṣāprāyaścittāni Sarvayajñānām Prāyaścittāni Anugrahāḥ&#xA;Somaprāyaścittāni&#xA;CONTENTS&#xA;PRAŠNA&#xA;XXVIII.9&#xA;vii&#xA;PAGES&#xA;1766-1769&#xA;XXVIII.10-11 XXVIII.12-13&#xA;1768-1771&#xA;1772-1777&#xA;XXIX. 1-2&#xA;1778-1783&#xA;Yajñakarmaņi Prāyaścittāni&#xA;XXIX.3-6&#xA;1782-1791&#xA;Agnihotrasya Laukikavidhiḥ&#xA;XXIX.7&#xA;1790-1793&#xA;Agnihotṛsamāsaḥ&#xA;XXIX.8-11&#xA;1792-1801&#xA;Prayaścittasamuccayaḥ&#xA;XXIX. 12-13&#xA;1800-1807&#xA;GLOSSARY&#xA;BIBLIOGRAPHY&#xA;1809-1837&#xA;1839-1844&#xA;ABBREVIATIONS&#xA;App&#xA;Apparently&#xA;Apastamba Śrautasūtra&#xA;ĀśvSS&#xA;Aśvalayana Śrautasūtra&#xA;AV&#xA;Atharvaveda Samhita&#xA;BaudhŚS&#xA;Baudhāyana Śrautasūtra&#xA;BhārŚS&#xA;DhS&#xA;GS&#xA;Grhya sūtra&#xA;JAOS&#xA;JBr&#xA;JBRAS&#xA;KausBr&#xA;Bharadvaja Śrautasūtra&#xA;Dharma Sūtra&#xA;Journal of American Oriental Society Jaiminiya Brāhmaṇa&#xA;Journal of Bombay Royal Asiatic Society Kauṣītaki Brāhmaṇa&#xA;Kāṭhaka Śrautasūtra Katyayana Śrautasūtra&#xA;Kath$S KatyŚS&#xA;KS&#xA;Kathaka Samhită&#xA;ManSS&#xA;Mānava Śrautasūtra&#xA;MS&#xA;Maitrāyaṇī Samhitā&#xA;MSS&#xA;RV&#xA;SadBr&#xA;ŚānkhGS&#xA;ŚBr&#xA;SuS&#xA;Manuscripts&#xA;Rgveda Samhitā&#xA;Şaḍvimsa Brāhmaṇa&#xA;Sankhayana Gṛhya Sūtra&#xA;Śatapatha Brāhmaṇa Śānkhāyana Sūtra Śulba Sūtra&#xA;TÄ&#xA;Taittiriya Aranyaka&#xA;TāndBr&#xA;TBr&#xA;Tāndya Brāhmaṇa Taittiriya Brāhmaṇa&#xA;TS&#xA;Taittiriya Samhitā&#xA;VādhŚS&#xA;Vādhūla Śrautasútra&#xA;VS&#xA;VSK&#xA;Vājasaneyi Samhitā&#xA;Vājasaneyi Samhitā Kāṇva&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
