<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Special Animal Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/1_The_Special_Animal_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/1_The_Special_Animal_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He who desires prosperity should offer a white (beast) to Vayu; Vayu is the swiftest deity; verily he has recourse to him with his own share; verily he makes him attain prosperity; he prospers. &amp;lsquo;He is an overswift deity,&amp;rsquo; they say, &amp;lsquo;he has power to burn him up.&amp;rsquo; This (beast) he should offer to Vayu of the team; the team is his support; verily, being supported he attains prosperity to avoid being burnt; he&lt;br&gt;&#xA;prospers [1]. He who desires a village should offer to Vayu of the team; Vayu leads these creatures tied by the nose; verily he has recourse to Vayu of the team with his own share; verily he assigns him creatures led by the nose; he becomes possessed of a village. It is offered to (Vayu) of the team; verily he makes creatures abide steadfast with him. He who desires offspring should offer to Vayu of the team; Vayu is expiration, the team is inspiration; expiration and inspiration depart from the offspring of him [2] who being fit for offspring yet obtains not offspring. Verily he has recourse to Vayu of the team with his own share; verily he for him begets offspring by means of expiration and inspiration; he obtains offspring. He who has long been ill should offer to Vayu of the team; Vayu is expiration, the team is inspiration, expiration and inspiration depart from him whose illness is long. Verily he has recourse to Vayu of the team with his own share [3], he bestows on him expiration and inspiration; even if his life be gone, he yet lives. Prajapati was here alone; he desired, &amp;lsquo;May I create offspring and cattle&amp;rsquo;; he took out from his body the omentum, and placed it in the fire. The hornless goat then came to life; he offered it to its own deity; then did he create offspring and cattle. He who desires offspring [4] and cattle should offer to Prajapati a hornless goat. Verily he has recourse to Prajapati with his own share; verily he begets for him offspring and cattle. The beard is the characteristic of man, the lack of horns of the horse, having incisors on one side only that of cattle, having sheep-like hooves that of sheep, the goat-nature that of goats; so many are the domesticated animals; verily by their characteristics he wins them [5]. He who desires cattle should offer one of a triplet to Soma and Pusan; the she-goat has two teats, two are born separately, the third for strength and growth. Verily he has recourse to Soma and Pusan with their own share; verily they produce cattle for him; Soma is the depositor of seed, Pusan the producer of cattle; Soma deposits seeds for him, Pusan produces cattle. The sacrificial post is of Udumbara; the Udumbara is strength, cattle are strength; verily by strength he wins for him strength and cattle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Special Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/2_The_Special_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/2_The_Special_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Prajapati created offspring. On their creation Indra and Agni hid them away. Prajapati reflected, &amp;lsquo;Indra and Agni have hidden away from me offspring.&amp;rsquo; He then perceived this offering to Indra and Agni on eleven potsherds, and offered it, and the two (gods) restored offspring to him. Indra and Agni indeed conceal his offspring, who being fit for offspring, yet obtains not offspring; so let a man who desires offspring offer a sacrifice to Indra, and Agni on eleven potsherds. Verily Indra and Agni [1] he has recourse to with their own share; verily they make manifest offspring to him, he obtains offspring.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;He should make an offering to Indra and Agni on eleven potsherds who has a dispute about a field or with his neighbours. Verily Indra and Agni he has recourse to with their own share, by means of them he over powers the power and strength of his rival, he overcomes the evil foe. Now power and strength depart from him who advances to battle; let him who is about to advance to battle offer to Indra and Agni an offering on eleven potsherds [2]. Verily Indra and Agni he has recourse to with their own share; verily they two place power and strength in him; with power and strength he approaches the battle and conquers in it. Now power and strength is he bereft of who wins a battle; let him who has won a battle make an offering to Indra and Agni on eleven potsherds. Verily Indra and Agni he has recourse to with their own share; verily they two place power and strength in him [3], he is not bereft of power and strength. Now power and strength depart from him who goes to the assembly; let him who is about to go to the assembly make an offering to Indra and Agni on eleven potsherds. Verily Indra and Agni he has recourse to with their own share; verily they two place power and strength in him, with power and strength he goes to the assembly. Let him next offer an oblation to Pusan. Pusan is the giver of power and strength, verily Pusan [4] he has recourse to with his own share; verily he gives to him power and strength. When he has gone to the assembly he should offer an oblation to Ksetrapati; Ksetrapati is this (earth); verily on this earth he takes firm root. Thereafter let him make the offering to Indra and Agni on eleven potsherds; verily taking stand on this earth he next places power and strength in his body.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Special Sacrifices (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/3_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/3_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He who desires prosperity should offer to the Adityas, giving prosperity; it is the Adityas who repel from prosperity him who being fit for prosperity does not obtain prosperity; verily he has recourse to the Adityas, giving prosperity, with their own share; verily they make him attain prosperity; he becomes prosperous. He who has been expelled or is being expelled should offer an oblation to the Adityas, the sustainers; the Adityas are the expellers, the Adityas are the procurers; verily he has recourse to the Adityas, the sustainers [1] with their own share; verily they support him in the people; he is unexpellable. &amp;lsquo;O Aditi, do thou confirm&amp;rsquo;, (with these words) be who is being expelled should take the foot (dust) of him (who is expelling him); Aditi is this (earth); verily she confirms the kingdom for him; &amp;lsquo;Be the blessing fulfilled&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he makes the blessing come true; &amp;lsquo;Mind here&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he makes the people of one mind with him; &amp;lsquo;Come hither, O ye Maruts [2] rich in dew, with this lord of the people against yon king&amp;rsquo;, he says; the people are connected with the Maruts, the lord of the people is the highest; verily he unites him with the people and the realm. From the house of a village judge further on he should take rice; he should separate out the white and the black; of the white he should offer an oblation to the Adityas; the people have the Adityas for their deity; verily he attains the people [3]; &amp;lsquo;The people he has attained, the realm he has not&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Special Sacrifices (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/4_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/4_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The gods, men, and the Pitrs were on one side, the Asuras, Raksases, and Piśacas on the other. Of the gods the little blood they drew the Raksases smothered by the nights and dawn dawned on them smothered and dead. The gods understood, &amp;lsquo;Him who of us dies, it is the Raksases who kill.&amp;rsquo; They invited the Raksases; they said, &amp;lsquo;Let us choose a boon; what [1] we win from the Asuras, let that be shared between us.&amp;rsquo; Then indeed did the gods conquer the Asuras, and having conquered the Asuras, they drove away the Raksases. The Raksases (saying), &amp;lsquo;Ye have done falsely&amp;rsquo;, surrounded the gods on all sides. The gods found a protector in Agni; they offered to Agni, the forward, a cake on eight potsherds, to Agni, the overcomer, to Agni with the face. In that they offered to Agni, the forward, the Raksases in front [2] they repelled thereby; in that (they offered) to Agni, the overcomer, the Raksases that were around they repelled thereby; in that (they offered) to Agni with the face, the Raksases behind were repelled thereby. That the gods prospered, the Raksases were defeated. He who has foes should in conflict sacrifice with this offering; he should offer to Agni, the forward, a cake on eight potsherds, to Agni, the overcomer [3], to Agni with the face. In that he offers to Agni, the forward, he repels thereby the foe who is superior to him; in that (he offers) to Agni, the overcomer, he repels thereby (the foe) who is equal to him; in that (he offers) to Agni with the face, he repels thereby the foe which is inferior to him. He repels the foe who is superior,&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The New and Full Moon Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/5_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/5_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The Part of the Hotr at the New and Full Moon Sacrifices&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;07&#34;&gt;07&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The gods could not rest on the Rc or the Yajus. On the Saman only could they rest. He makes the noise &amp;lsquo;Him&amp;rsquo;; verily he makes the Saman. He makes the noise &amp;lsquo;Him&amp;rsquo;; where the gods rested, there he sets them in motion. He makes the noise &amp;lsquo;Him&amp;rsquo;; this is the yoking of speech. He makes the noise &amp;lsquo;Him&amp;rsquo;; thus the sacrificers produce offspring. He repeats the first (verse) thrice, the last thrice; verily he ties the end of the sacrifice [1] so that it may not slip. He repeats (it) continuously, for the continuity of the breaths and of food, and for the smiting away of the Raksases. The first he repeats is connected with the Rathantara (Saman), this world is connected with the Rathantara; verily he conquers this world. He divides it thrice; these worlds are three; verily he conquers these worlds. The last he repeats is connected with the Brhat (Saman); yonder world is connected with the Brhat; verily he conquers yonder world. &amp;lsquo;Forward [2] your viands&amp;rsquo;, he repeats, a verse which has not any indication (of its deity) and (therefore) is addressed to Prajapati. Prajapati is the sacrifice; verily he grasps the sacrifice as Prajapati. &amp;lsquo;Forward your viands&amp;rsquo;, he repeats; viands are food; verily he wins food. &amp;lsquo;Forward your viands&amp;rsquo;, he repeats; therefore seed is deposited in front. &amp;lsquo;O Agni, come hither for the feast&amp;rsquo;, he repeats; therefore offspring are born at the back. &amp;lsquo;Forward your viands&amp;rsquo;, he repeats [3]; &amp;lsquo;viands&amp;rsquo; are the months, &amp;lsquo;heavenwards&amp;rsquo; are the half-months, &amp;lsquo;rich in the oblation&amp;rsquo; are the gods, &amp;lsquo;full of butter&amp;rsquo; is the cow, &amp;lsquo;he goes to the gods&amp;rsquo; (that is) the sacrifice, &amp;lsquo;desirous of favour &amp;rsquo; is the sacrificer. &amp;lsquo;Thou art this, thou art this&amp;rsquo;, (with these words) he wins the dear abode of the sacrifice. If he desire for a man, &amp;lsquo;May he live all his days&amp;rsquo;, he should repeat for him &amp;lsquo;Forward your viands&amp;rsquo;, and then continuously the next half-verse of &amp;lsquo;Agni, come hither to the feast&amp;rsquo; [4]. Verily by expiration does he make steadfast his inspiration, and he lives all his days. He, who knows the elbow of the Samidhenis, puts his enemy in his elbow. He joins the half-verses; this is the elbow of the Samidhenis; he who knows thus puts his foe in his elbow. The Samidhenis were brought out by Rsi after Rsi; if they were not connected together, they would go away from the sacrificer&amp;rsquo;s offspring&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 The New and Full Moon Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/6_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/2/6_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Part of the Hotr in the New and Full Moon Sacrifice&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;07&#34;&gt;07&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Manu desired what of earth was sacrificial. He found the poured out ghee. He said, &amp;lsquo;Who is able to produce this also at the sacrifice?&amp;rsquo; Mitra and Varuna said, &amp;lsquo;We are able to produce the cow.&amp;rsquo; Then they set the cow in motion. Wherever she stepped, there ghee was pressed out; therefore she is called ghee-footed; that is her origin. &amp;lsquo;The Rathantara is invoked with the earth&amp;rsquo;, he says [1]. The Rathantara is this (earth); verily he invokes her with food. &amp;lsquo;The Vamadevya is invoked with the atmosphere&amp;rsquo;, he says. The Vamadevya, is cattle; verily he invokes cattle with the atmosphere. &amp;lsquo;The Brhat is invoked with the sky&amp;rsquo;, he says. The Brhat is connected with food; verily he invokes food with the sky. &amp;rsquo; The seven Hotras are invoked&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he invokes the Hotras. &amp;lsquo;The cow is invoked with the bull&amp;rsquo;, he says [2]; verily he invokes a pair. &amp;lsquo;The friend food is invoked&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he invokes the Soma drink. &amp;lsquo;It is invoked; ho!&amp;rsquo; he says; verily he invokes the self, for the self is the best of those invoked. He invokes food, food is cattle; verily he invokes cattle. He invokes four, for cattle are four-footed. &amp;lsquo;Offspring of Manu&amp;rsquo;, he says, for Manu first saw her [3]. &amp;lsquo;Ghee footed&amp;rsquo;, he says. Because ghee was pressed out of her foot, therefore be says thus. &amp;lsquo;Of Mitra and Varuna&amp;rsquo;, he says, for Mitra and Varuna set her in motion. &amp;lsquo;The Brahman, god made, is invoked&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he invokes the Brahman. &amp;lsquo;The divine Adhvaryus are invoked, the human are invoked&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he invokes the gods and men. &amp;lsquo;Who shall help this sacrifice and make the lord of the sacrifice prosper&amp;rsquo;, he says [4]; verily he invokes a blessing for the sacrifice and the sacrificer. &amp;lsquo;Sky and earth are invoked&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he invokes sky and earth. &amp;lsquo;Born of yore, the righteous&amp;rsquo;, he says, for they were born of yore and are righteous. &amp;lsquo;Divine, with gods for children&amp;rsquo;, he says, for they are divine and have gods for children. &amp;lsquo;Invoked is this sacrificer&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he invokes the sacrificer. &amp;lsquo;Invoked in the highest sacrifice, invoked in the greater offering, invoked in the divine abode&amp;rsquo; [5], he says. The highest sacrifice is offspring, the greater offering is cattle, the divine abode&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
