<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;6 THE EXPLANATION OF THE SOMA SACRIFICE on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;6 THE EXPLANATION OF THE SOMA SACRIFICE on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifce</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/1_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/1_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifce/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He makes a hall with beams pointing east. The gods and men divided the quarters, the gods (obtained) the eastern, the Pitrs the southern, men the western, the Rudras the northern. In that he makes a hall with beams pointing east, the sacrificer approaches the world of the gods. He covers it over, for the world of the gods is hidden from the world of men. &amp;lsquo;It is not easy&amp;rsquo;, they say, &amp;rsquo;to go from this world; for who knows if he is in yonder world or not.&amp;rsquo; He makes at the corners apertures [1], for the winning of both worlds. He shaves his hair and beard, he trims his nails. The hair and the beard are dead and impure skin, and by thus destroying the dead and impure skin he becomes fit for the sacrifice and approaches the sacrifice. The Angirases going to the world of heaven placed in the waters consecration and penance. He bathes in the waters; verily visibly he secures consecration and penance. He bathes at a ford, for at a ford did they place (consecration and penance); he bathes at a ford [2]; verily he becomes a ford for his fellows. He sips water; verily he becomes pure within. He consecrates him with a garment; the linen garment has Soma for its deity. He who consecrates himself approaches Soma as his deity. He says, &amp;lsquo;Thou art the body of Soma; guard my body.&amp;rsquo; He approaches his own deity; verily also he invokes this blessing. (Of the garment) the place where the border is belongs to Agni, the wind-guard to Vayu, the fringe to the Pitrs, the foreedge to the plants [3], the warp to the Adityas, the woof to the All-gods, the meshes to the Naksatras. The garment is thus connected with all the gods; in that he consecrates him with the garment, verily with all the gods he consecrates him. Man has breath without; his eating is his breath, he eats; verily he consecrates himself with breath. He becomes satiated. As great as is his breath, with it he approaches the sacrifice. Ghee pertains to the gods, sour cream to the Pitrs, well-seasoned butter to men [4], fresh butter is connected with all the gods; verily in anointing with fresh butter he satisfies all the gods. The man who is consecrated has fallen from this world and yet not gone to the world of the gods; fresh butter is as it were midway; therefore he anoints with fresh butter, along the hair, with a Yajus, for destruction. Indra slew Vrtra; his eyeball fell away; it became collyrium. When he anoints, verily he takes away the eye of his enemy. He anoints his right eye first [5], for men anoint the left first. He does not rub (the ointment) on, for men rub (the ointment) on. Five times he anoints; the Pankti has five syllables, the sacrifice is fivefold; verily he obtains the sacrifice. He anoints a limited number of times, for men anoint an unlimited number of times. He anoints with (a stalk) which has a tuft, for men anoint with (a stalk) which has no tuft; (verily he anoints them) for discrimination. If he were to anoint with (a stalk) having no tuft, he would be as it were a thunder bolt. He anoints with one which has a tuft, for friendship [6]. Indra slew Vrtra, he died upon the waters. Of the waters what was fit for sacrifice, pure, and divine, that went out of the waters, and became Darbha grass. In that he purifies (the sacrificer) with bunches of Darbha grass, verily he purifies him with the waters which are fit for sacrifice, pure, and divine. He purifies (him) with two (stalks); verily he purifies him by days and nights. He purifies (him) with three (stalks); three are these worlds; verily he purifies him by these worlds. He purifies (him) with five stalks [7]; the Pankti has five syllables, the sacrifice is fivefold; verily he purifies him by the sacrifice. He purifies (him) with six (stalks); six are the seasons; verily he purifies him by the seasons. He purifies (him) with seven (stalks); seven are the metres; verily he purifies him by the metres. He purifies (him) with nine (stalks); nine are the breaths in man; verily he purifies him along with his breaths. He purifies (him) with twenty-one (stalks); there are ten fingers and ten toes, and the body is the twenty&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/2_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/2_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If he should offer hospitality after unyoking both (the oxen), he would break up the sacrifice. If (he should offer) before he has unyoked both, it would be as when hospitality is offered to one who has&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;not yet arrived. One ox is unyoked, one ox is not unyoked; then he offers hospitality, for the continuance of the sacrifice. The wife (of the sacrificer) holds on (to the cart); for the wife is mistress of the household gear; verily he offers what is approved by the wife. The share of the wife in the sacrifice makes a pair; so the wife also [1] grasps the sacrifice that it may not be interrupted. With whatever retinue the king comes, to all of them hospitality is offered; the metres are the retinue of King Soma. &amp;lsquo;Thou art the hospitality of Agni. For Visnu thee!&amp;rsquo; he says; thus he offers (hospitality) to the Gayatri. &amp;lsquo;Thou art the hospitality of Soma. &amp;lsquo;For Visnu thee!&amp;rsquo; he says; thus he offers (hospitality) to the Tristubh. &amp;lsquo;Thou art the hospitality of the stranger. For Visnu thee!&amp;rsquo; he says; thus he offers (hospitality) to the Jagati [2]. &amp;lsquo;For Agni thee, giver of wealth, for Visnu thee!&amp;rsquo; he says; thus he offers (hospitality) to the Anustubh. &amp;lsquo;For the eagle, bringer of the Soma, thee, for Visnu thee!&amp;rsquo; he says; thus he offers (hospitality) to the Gayatri. He offers five times. The Pankti has five syllables, the sacrifice is fivefold; verily he wins the sacrifice. The theologians say, &amp;lsquo;For what reason is the Gayatri offered to on either side of the offering of hospitality?&amp;rsquo; Because the Gayatri brought the Soma down [3]; therefore is it offered to on both sides of hospitality, before and after. Hospitality is the head of the sacrifice, the sacrificial cake is offered on nine potsherds, therefore the head has nine apertures. The sacrificial cake is offered on nine potsherds. The three sets of three potsherds are commensurate with the Trivrt Stoma, the Trivrt is brilliance; verily he places brilliance in the head of the sacrifice. The sacrificial cake is offered on nine potsherds. The three sets of three potsherds are commensurate with the threefold breath, the breath is threefold [4]; verily in order he places the threefold breath in the head of the sacrifice. Now the Saccharum spontaneum shoots are the eyelashes of Prajapati, and his lids are pieces of sugar-cane. In that the strew is of Saccharum spontaneum and the dividing-stakes of sugar-cane, verily he brings together the eye of Prajapati. Now the libations made by the gods the Asuras tore and ate. The gods saw the Gmelina arborea tree. (Thinking) &amp;lsquo;It is fit for work; by it one can perform work&amp;rsquo;, they made the enclosing sticks of Gmelina arborea wood [5], and by them they smote away the Raksases. In that the enclosing-sticks are made of Gmelina arborea wood, it is for the smiting away of the Raksases. He makes them touch, that the Raksases may not go through them. He does not place one in front, for the sun which rises in front smites away the Raksases. He places the kindling-sticks erect; verily from above he smites away the Raksases; (he places one) with a Yajus, the other in silence, to make a pair. He places two; the sacrifice has two feet; (verily they serve) for support. The theologians say [6], &amp;lsquo;There are both Agni and Soma here; why is hospitality offered to Soma and not to Agni?&amp;rsquo; In that having kindled fire he places it on the fire, by that verily is hospitality offered to Agni. Or rather they say, &amp;lsquo;Agni is all the gods.&amp;rsquo; In that he kindles fire after placing the oblation, he thus produces all the gods for the oblation when it has been placed.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/3_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/3_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the pit he scatters (earth) on the altars; the pit is the birthplace of the sacrifice; (verily it serves) to unite the sacrifice with its birthplace. The gods lost by conquest the sacrifice; they won it again from the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar; the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar is the invincible part of the sacrifice. In that he draws off the altar fires from that of the Agnidh, he renews the sacrifice from the invincible part of it. Conquered as it were they go who creep to the Bahispavamana (Stotra) when the Bahispavamana has been sung [1], he says, &amp;lsquo;Agnidh, draw off the fires, spread the strew, make ready the sacrificial cake.&amp;rsquo; Verily having re-won the sacrifice they keep renewing it. At two pressings he draws off by means of embers, at the third with (flaming) splinters, to give it glory verily he completes it. The altars guarded the Soma in yonder world they took away the Soma from them; they followed it and surrounded it. He who knows thus [2] wins an attendant. They were deprived of the Soma drink; they besought the gods for the Soma drink; the gods said to them, &amp;lsquo;Take two names each; then shall ye gain it, or not.&amp;rsquo; Then the altars became fires (also); therefore a Brahman who has two names is likely to prosper. Those which came nearest gained the Soma drink viz. the Ahavaniya, the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar, the Hotr&amp;rsquo;s, and the Marjaliya; therefore they sacrifice on them. He leaves them out in uttering the cry for sacrifice, for [3] they were deprived of the Soma drink. The gods drove away the Asuras who were in front by the sacrifices which they offered on the eastern side, and the Asuras who were behind by those which they offered on the western side. Soma libations are offered in the east, seated to the west he besprinkles the altars; verily from behind and from in front the sacrificer smites away his enemies; therefore offspring are engendered behind, and are brought forth in front [4]. The altars are the breaths; if the Adhvaryu were to go past the altars to the west, he would mingle the breaths, he would be liable to die. The Hotr is the navel of the sacrifice; the expiration is above the navel, the inspiration is below; if the Adhvaryu were to go past the Hotr to the west, he would place the expiration in the inspiration, he would be liable to die. The Adhvaryu should not accompany the song; the Adhvaryu&amp;rsquo;s strength is his voice; if the Adhvaryu were to accompany the song, he would confer his voice on the Udgatr [5], and his voice would fail. The theologians say, &amp;lsquo;The Adhvaryu should not go beyond the Sadas to the west before the Soma offering is completed. Then how is he to go to offer the sacrifices in the southern fire? Because that is the end of the fires. But how are the gods to know whether it is the end or not?&amp;rsquo; He goes round the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar to the north and offers the sacrifices in the southern fire; verily he does not mingle the breaths. Some of the altars are besprinkled, some not; those which he besprinkles he delights; those which he does not besprinkle he delights by indicating them.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Exposition Of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/4_The_Exposition_Of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/4_The_Exposition_Of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;By means of the sacrifice Prajapati created offspring; verily he created them by the subsidiary sacrifices; in that he offers the subsidiary sacrifices, verily thus the sacrificer creates offspring. He cuts off from the hind portion, for from the hind portion offspring are born; he cuts off from the thick side, for offspring are born from the thick side; he cuts off without confusion, to prevent confusion of the vital airs. He does not turn (it) round; if he were to turn (it) round, disease would be likely to seize his offspring. &amp;lsquo;Go to the ocean, hail!&amp;rsquo; he says verily thus he produces seed [1]. &amp;lsquo;Go&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/5_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/5_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Indra raised his bolt to hurl at Vrtra; Vrtra was afraid of the bolt when raised to be hurled; he said, &amp;lsquo;Hurl it not at me; there is this strength in me, that will I bestow on thee&amp;rsquo;; on him he bestowed the Ukthya. At him he raised (the bolt) to hurl a second time; he said, &amp;lsquo;Hurl it not at me; there is this strength in me, that will I bestow on thee&amp;rsquo; [1]; on him he bestowed again the Ukthya. At him he raised (the bolt) to hurl a third time; Visnu supported him (saying), &amp;lsquo;Smite&amp;rsquo;; he said, &amp;lsquo;Hurl it not at me; there is this strength in me, that will I bestow on thee&amp;rsquo;; he bestowed on him again the Ukthya. Him when he had lost his magic power he slew, for the sacrifice was his magic power. In that the Ukthya is drawn, verily the sacrificer thus appropriates the power [2] and strength of his foe. &amp;lsquo;To Indra thee, to him of the Brhat, the strong&amp;rsquo;, he says, for to Indra he gave it; &amp;rsquo;to him thee! To Visnu thee!&amp;rsquo; he says; in that Visnu supported him (saying), &amp;lsquo;Strike&amp;rsquo;, he gives Visnu a share therein. Thrice he draws, for thrice he gave to him., This is thy birthplace; thou art the renewed offering&amp;rsquo;, he says, for repeatedly [3] he draws from it. The Ukthya is the eye of the sacrifice; therefore the Somas follow the Ukthya when offered; therefore the body follows the eye; therefore as one goes many follow; therefore one becomes superior among many; therefore one wins many wives. If the Adhvaryu desire, &amp;lsquo;May I bestow upon myself the glory of the sacrifice&amp;rsquo;, standing between the Ahavaniya and the oblation-holder he should pour (it) down [4]; verily he bestows upon himself the glory of the sacrifice. If he desire, &amp;lsquo;May I bestow upon the sacrificer the glory of the sacrifice&amp;rsquo;, he should pour (it) down standing between the Sadas and the oblation-holder; verily he bestows upon the sacrificer the glory of the sacrifice. If he desire, &amp;lsquo;May I bestow upon the Sadasyas the glory of the sacrifice&amp;rsquo;, he should pour (it) down, grasping the Sadas; verily he bestows upon the Sadasyas the glory of the sacrifice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 The Exposition of the Daksina and other Offerings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/6_The_Exposition_of_the_Daksina_and_other_Offerings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/6_The_Exposition_of_the_Daksina_and_other_Offerings/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The sacrifices with the gifts are offered for the world of heaven. He offers with two (verses) on the Garhapatya; the sacrificer has two feet; (verily it serves) for support. He offers in the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar; verily he ascends the atmosphere. He approaches the Sadas; verily he makes him go to the world of heaven. He offers in the Garhapatya with verses addressed to Surya; verily he makes him mount&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
