<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;अधिस्रोतः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;अधिस्रोतः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Gardner-परिचयः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/gardner-parichayaH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/gardner-parichayaH/</guid>
      <description>Source: TW
Text history This text of the Shatapatha, Maadhyandina Shaakha, was encoded in 1971 +++(based on Weber)+++, partly funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities, by Dr. H. S. Ananthanarayana under the direction of Dr. W. P. Lehmann. It is painstakingly reconstructed and accessible in a multitude of ways.
Gretil note On the basis of the edition by Albrecht Weber, The Çatapatha-Brāhmaṇa in the Mādhyandina-Çākhā with extracts from the commentaries of Sāyaṇa, Harisvāmin and Dvivedānga, Berlin 1849 / Repr.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Svaras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/gardner_svaras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/gardner_svaras/</guid>
      <description>Accent in the e-text of the Shatapath BrAhmaNa
Traditionally, the Shatapatha is considered in its mss. to have underscore (&amp;quot;_&amp;quot;) markings for udaatta. But, as noted, among others, by Hoffman 1 the marking denotes anudaatta. Much of the confusion arises because the mss. show markings of only one kind, that of the understroke. The challenge has been to derive the traditional threefold accentuation scheme of udaatta, anudaatta, svarita, from this rarified notation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Weber intro</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/weber_intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/mAdhyandinam/shatapatha-brAhmaNam/meta/weber-srotaH/meta/weber_intro/</guid>
      <description>This edition of the Brâhmanas of the white Yajurveda is destined only to comprehend the text. An introductory essay, a glossary, a partial translation and deeper researches into all the materials, treasured up here and in the sútras of Kútyayana, shall follow in a separate work on the Yajur-Vedic ceremonies. Therefore I shall here content myself with enumerating the critical apparatus, exstant in Europe, and giving a short explanation of the accents.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
