<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;2 on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;2 on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Special Animal Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/1_The_Special_Animal_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/1_The_Special_Animal_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>01 He who desires prosperity should offer a white (beast) to Vayu; Vayu is the swiftest deity; verily he has recourse to him with his own share; verily he makes him attain prosperity; he prospers. &amp;lsquo;He is an overswift deity,&amp;rsquo; they say, &amp;lsquo;he has power to burn him up.&amp;rsquo; This (beast) he should offer to Vayu of the team; the team is his support; verily, being supported he attains prosperity to avoid being burnt; he</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Special Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/2_The_Special_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/2_The_Special_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>01 Prajapati created offspring. On their creation Indra and Agni hid them away. Prajapati reflected, &amp;lsquo;Indra and Agni have hidden away from me offspring.&amp;rsquo; He then perceived this offering to Indra and Agni on eleven potsherds, and offered it, and the two (gods) restored offspring to him. Indra and Agni indeed conceal his offspring, who being fit for offspring, yet obtains not offspring; so let a man who desires offspring offer a sacrifice to Indra, and Agni on eleven potsherds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Special Sacrifices (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/3_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/3_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 He who desires prosperity should offer to the Adityas, giving prosperity; it is the Adityas who repel from prosperity him who being fit for prosperity does not obtain prosperity; verily he has recourse to the Adityas, giving prosperity, with their own share; verily they make him attain prosperity; he becomes prosperous. He who has been expelled or is being expelled should offer an oblation to the Adityas, the sustainers; the Adityas are the expellers, the Adityas are the procurers; verily he has recourse to the Adityas, the sustainers [1] with their own share; verily they support him in the people; he is unexpellable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Special Sacrifices (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/4_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/4_The_Special_Sacrifices_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 The gods, men, and the Pitrs were on one side, the Asuras, Raksases, and Piśacas on the other. Of the gods the little blood they drew the Raksases smothered by the nights and dawn dawned on them smothered and dead. The gods understood, &amp;lsquo;Him who of us dies, it is the Raksases who kill.&amp;rsquo; They invited the Raksases; they said, &amp;lsquo;Let us choose a boon; what [1] we win from the Asuras, let that be shared between us.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 The New and Full Moon Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/5_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/5_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>01 a Viśvarupa, son of Tvastr, was the domestic priest of the gods, and the sister&amp;rsquo;s son of the Asuras. He had three heads, one which drank Soma, one Sura, and one which ate food. He promised openly the share to the gods, secretly to the Asuras. Men promise openly the share to every one; if they promise any one secretly, his share is indeed promised. Therefore Indra was afraid (thinking), &amp;lsquo;Such an one is diverting the sovereignty (from me).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 The New and Full Moon Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/6_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/2/6_The_New_and_Full_Moon_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>01 He offers to the kindling-sticks; verily he wins spring among the seasons. He offers to Tanunapat; verily he wins the hot season. He offers to the oblations; verily he wins the rains. He offers to the sacrificial strew, verily lie wins autumn. He offers with the cry of &amp;lsquo;Hail!&amp;rsquo;; verily he wins the winter. Therefore in winter animals over which the cry of &amp;lsquo;Hail!&amp;rsquo; is raised perish. He offers to the kindling sticks; verily he wins the dawns of the goddesses.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
