<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;4 THE PILING OF THE FIRE ALTAR on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;4 THE PILING OF THE FIRE ALTAR on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Placing of the Fire in the Fire-pan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/1_The_Placing_of_the_Fire_in_the_Fire-pan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/1_The_Placing_of_the_Fire_in_the_Fire-pan/</guid>
      <description>01 a Yoking mind first,
Extending his thoughts, Savitr
Discerning the light,
Hath brought Agni from the earth.
b Yoking with mind the gods,
Going to the heaven, the sky, with thought,
Those that are to make great light,
Savitr instigates.
c With mind well yoked are we
In the instigation of god Savitr,
For strength to go to the heaven.
d They yoke their minds, they yoke their thoughts,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Preparation of the Ground for the Fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/2_The_Preparation_of_the_Ground_for_the_Fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/2_The_Preparation_of_the_Ground_for_the_Fire/</guid>
      <description>01 a Thou art the step of Visnu, overcoming hostility, mount the Gayatri metre, step along the earth, excluded is he whom we hate. Thou art the step of Visnu, overcoming imprecations, mount the Tristubh metre, step along the atmosphere, excluded is he whom we hate. Thou art the step of Visnu, overcomer of the enemy, mount the Jagati metre, step along the sky, excluded is he whom we hate. Thou art the stop of Visnu [1], overcomer of the foe, mount the Anustubh metre, step along the quarters, excluded is he whom we hate.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Five Layers of Bricks</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/3_The_Five_Layers_of_Bricks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/3_The_Five_Layers_of_Bricks/</guid>
      <description>01 a I place thee in the going of the waters; I place thee in the rising of the waters; I place thee in the ashes of the waters; I place thee in the light of the waters; I place thee in the movement of the waters.
b Sit on the billows as thy place of rest; sit on the ocean as thy place of rest; sit on the stream as thy place of rest; sit in the abode of the waters; sit on the seat of the waters.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Fifth Layer of Bricks (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/4_The_Fifth_Layer_of_Bricks_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/4_The_Fifth_Layer_of_Bricks_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 a Thou art the ray; for dwelling thee! Quicken the dwelling. Thou art advance; for right thee! Quicken right. Thou art following; for sky thee! Quicken the sky. Thou art union; for atmosphere thee! Quicken the atmosphere. Thou art propping; for earth thee! Quicken earth. Thou art a prop; for rain thee! Quicken rain. Thou art blowing forward; for day thee! Quicken day.
b Thou art blowing after; for night thee!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 The Offerings to Rudra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/5_The_Offerings_to_Rudra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/5_The_Offerings_to_Rudra/</guid>
      <description>03 a Homage to the strong, the piercing, to the lord of assailers homage!
b Homage to the leader, the holder of the quiver, to the lord of thieves homage!
c Homage to the holder of the quiver, to the owner of the quiver, to the lord of robbers homage!
d Homage to the cheater, the swindler, to the lord of burglars homage!
c Homage to the glider, to the wanderer around, to the lord of the forests homage!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 The Preparation of the Fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/6_The_Preparation_of_the_Fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/6_The_Preparation_of_the_Fire/</guid>
      <description>01 a The strength resting on the stone, the bill,
On the wind, on Parjanya, on the breath of Varuna,
Brought together from the waters, from the plants, from the trees;
That food and strength do ye, O Maruts, bounteously bestow upon us.
b In the stone is thy hunger; let thy pain reach N. N., whom we hate.
c With the wind of the ocean
We envelop thee, O Agni;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 The Piling of the Fire Altar (Continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/7_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_Continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/4_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/7_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_Continued/</guid>
      <description>01 a O Agni and Visnu, may these songs gladden you in unison; come ye with radiance and strength.
b May for me strength, instigation, influence, inclination, thought, inspiration, speech, fame, renown, reputation, light, heaven, expiration, inspiration [1], cross-breathing, breath, mind, learning, voice, mind, eye, ear, skill, might, force, strength, life, old age, breath, body, protection, guard, limbs, bones, joints, bodies (prosper through the sacrifice).
02 May for me pre-eminence, overlordship, spirit, anger, violence, impetuosity, victorious power, greatness, breadth, extent, greatness, length, growth, growing, truth, faith, world [1], wealth, power,</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
