<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;शुल्ब-सूत्राणि on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;शुल्ब-सूत्राणि on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sen, Bag - Commentary</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sen_bAg_commentary/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sen_bAg_commentary/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;dc-&#34;&gt;CHAPTER 1&#xA;DRAWING OF EAST-WEST LINE, CONSTRUCTION OF SQUARES AND&#xA;FIXING THE PLACES OF THE AHAVANĪYA, GĀRHAPATYA, DAKSINĀGNI AND UTKARA ALTARS&#xA;The Katyayana-sulbasutra, in six chapters, is essentially a geometrical work containing the main principles of geometry and some problems involved in altar construction. Kātyāyana has made some reference to different vedis and agnis without any details of their construction with bricks and tried to explain geometrical results as such. In this chapter he has dealt with the method of drawing east-west and north-south lines, the construction of squares and the determination of the relative positions of ahavaniya, gārhapatya, dakṣiṇāgni and utkara altars.&#xA;DRAWING OF East-West anD THE NORTH-SOUTH LINES&#xA;1.2. Let O be the pole, and a circle EPW be drawn with a cord of length equal to OP.&#xA;NX&#xA;E&#xA;W&#xA;Fig. 1.&#xA;Let E and W be the eastern and western shadow points on the equinoctial day of the pole fixed at 0 (Fig. 1). Apte suggests that the actual east-west line was determined by the shadow of the pole on the equinox day and verified by the rising and setting points of the star Kṛttikā. Then EW is in east-west or prăci line. Two knots are given at the two ends of a cord which is double of the original cord and are fastened at the poles at E and W. The cord is then stretched towards north by its middle point and a mark N is given at it. This is the north point. Similarly south&#xA;■ Apte, 1-16&#xA;COMMENTARY&#xA;265&#xA;point S is obtained. Then NS, gives the north-south line. In the Sulbasūtras the east- west line has always been drawn first presumably because of the importance attached to this direction.&#xA;CONSTRUCTION of a Square or a Rectangle&#xA;1.3 This gives a general method of construction of a square or a rectangle. In a given cord marks are given for śroņi, amsa and nirañchana points. Two knots are fixed at the two ends of the cord; then fixing the two ends of the cord to the poles at the two ends of the east-west line, the cord is drawn by the nirañchana mark on either side of the line. By interchanging the knots at the two ends, the operation is repeated. Further details as to the length of the cord corresponding to a given distance between the two poles (the length of the altar) and where the nirañchana mark is to be given are discussed in the subsequent rules.&#xA;1.4-1.9. Rules 1.4 and 1.5 give direction for determining the nirañchana points and are used for the construction of square and rectangles.&#xA;First cord. Let AB, the given measure be a, BC, the added length a, and D, the nirañchana mark (Fig. 2(a)) so that&#xA;BC&#xA;a&#xA;BD&#xA;4&#xA;4&#xA;5a&#xA;By definition,&#xA;AD the diagonal&#xA;4&#xA;3a&#xA;and&#xA;DC =&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;the breadth&#xA;4&#xA;Clearly,&#xA;AD2&#xA;DC2&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sen, Bag - Translation</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sen_bAg_translation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sen_bAg_translation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1&#xA;1.1&#xA;1.2&#xA;1.3&#xA;1.4&#xA;1.5&#xA;1.6&#xA;1.7&#xA;1.8&#xA;We shall explain (the method of measuring areas by) the combination of the cords.&#xA;Having put a pole on a level ground and described a circle round it by means of a cord (fastened to the pole), a pole is fixed on each of the two points where the end of the pole&amp;rsquo;s shadow touches (the two halves of the circle). This (line joining the two points) is the east-west line (prācī). Then after doubling (a given) cord, two loops (made at its two ends) are fixed at the two poles (of the prāci), and (the cord is stretched towards south by its middle point where) a pole is fixed; the same is repeated to the north. This (line joining the two poles) is the north-south line (udīcī).&#xA;Two loops are fixed at the two ends of a cord. Marks are (to be given) at the fronis, the amsas, the nirañchana and the samāsabhangas. A pole is fixed at each end of the east-west line (of desired length); likewise (a pole is fixed at each of) the two froņis (west corners) and the two amsas (east corners). Having fixed the loops at the two poles (on the east-west line), the cord is to be stretched by the nirañchana mark towards the south-east corner. The same is done towards the north-east corner. After interchanging (the loops of the cord on the poles), the same is repeated. This is the method (of construction of squares and rectangles) in all cases.&#xA;Having doubled (the length of) a given measure, a mark is made at one- fourth of the added length; this is the nirañchana mark. (The length upto the nirañchana is) the diagonal (akṣṇayā) and the remainder the breadth (tiryaňmānī).&#xA;Or else, half the measure is added (to the measure) and a mark is made at the sixth part of the added length; this is the nirañchana. (The length up to the nirañchana is) the diagonal and the remainder the breadth.&#xA;For (constructing) a square (samacaturaśra), a pole (is to be fixed) at half the measure. For (constructing) a rectangle (dirghacaturaśra), (the pole is to be fixed) at half (of the value) prescribed in the text. The same is for (the construction of) a triangle (śakaṭa-mukha).&#xA;By these (methods) are explained the measurements of the sacrificial chamber (prāgvamśa), the altars, as also the other chambers (śālā). In these cases the north-south line (is used in the same manner) as in the east-west line. The same is for the sadas (tent).&#xA;By the word aparimita is to be meant a measure greater than the given&#xA;measure.&#xA;1.9&#xA;1.10&#xA;TRANSLATION&#xA;121&#xA;For decrease (nirhāsa) or increase (vṛddhi) as also for addition, the method according to the direction of the text is to be followed.&#xA;We shall explain in what follows how to find the southern agni by (the method of) the third. (A cord of a length equal to) the distance between the garhapatya and the āhavaniya is increased by one-sixth or one-seventh (of its length) and the length so increased is divided into three equal parts; the cord is stretched towards the south by the mark given at one-third from the other (western) end; at the point (thus obtained) the fire (is to be placed). The opposite point in the north is the place for the utkara (pit).&#xA;1.11 Alternately, with a cord of length equal to the distance (between the āhavaniya and the gārhapatya fire) reduced by one-third, a square is drawn in the eastern half; the fire (dakṣiṇāgni) (is placed) at the śroņi (that is, at the south-western corner of the square). By reversing, the rubbish heap (utkara) (is placed) at the amsa (that is, at the north-east corner).&#xA;2.1&#xA;2.2&#xA;2.3&#xA;2.4&#xA;2.5&#xA;2.6&#xA;2.7&#xA;2.8&#xA;2.9&#xA;2&#xA;(The fire-altar is) measured by the units of a chariot expressed in angulas; 188 angulas make one iṣā (pole); 104 angulas make one akṣa (axle of a cart); 86 angulas make one yuga (yoke); and 32 angulas make one famyā.&#xA;For (the construction of) the paitṛki (vedi), a square of 2 purusas (in area) is constructed and a pole is fixed at the middle of each side; this is the solution.&#xA;(The terms) karaṇī, tatkaraṇī, tiryanmānī, pārśvamānī and akṣṇayā denote cords (measuring the sides of the areas).&#xA;The diagonal (of a right triangle) of which the breadth is pada and the length 3 padas is √/10 padas.&#xA;Similarly, the diagonal (of a right triangle) of which the breadth is 2 padas and the length 6 padas is √40 padas.&#xA;The&#xA;juga and the samya measures as seen (in the case of the uttara vedi) have already been stated.&#xA;The (area of the) square drawn on the diagonal of a rectangle is equal to the sum of (areas of) the squares drawn separately on its breadth and length; this is the property of plane figures (concerning rectangles).&#xA;The diagonal of a square produces a square twice as large (that is, the diagonal equals √2 times the side of the square).&#xA;The measure is to be increased by its third and this (third) again by its own fourth less the thirtyfourth part (of that fourth); this is the (the value of) diagonal of a square (whose side is the measure); this is approximate.&#xA;122&#xA;KATYAYANA-SULBASŪTRA&#xA;2.10 The diagonal (of a rectangle) of which the breadth is the side of a given square (pramāṇa) and the length the side of a square twice as large (dvikaraṇī) equals the side of a square thrice as large (trkaraṇī).&#xA;2.11&#xA;Thereby is explained the side of a square one-third the area of a given square (tṛtīyakaraṇī). It is the side of a square one-ninth the area of the square thrice as large (tṛkarani). (Alternatively,) the side of three-ninth the square of the original (pramāņa) equals the side of a square one-third the area of a given square (tṛtiyakarani).&#xA;2.12 The side of a square one-third the area of a given square (tṛtiyakaraṇī) in&#xA;prakrama is used in (the construction of) the sautrāmaṇi (sacrificial altar).&#xA;2.13 (By the preceding rules) the combination of squares of equal size is explained. To find a combination of two squares of different measures, a (rectangular) part is cut off from the larger (square) with the side of the smaller; the diagonal of the cut-off (rectangular) part is the side of the combined&#xA;square.&#xA;3.1&#xA;3.2&#xA;3.3&#xA;3.4&#xA;3.5&#xA;3.6&#xA;3&#xA;If it is desired to remove a square from another, a (rectangular) part is cut off from the larger (square) with the side of the smaller one (to be removed); two poles are fixed on (two ends of) the cut and the line (thus obtained by joining the poles) is placed across so as to touch the opposite side; by this contact (the side) is cut off. With the cut-off (part) the difference (of two squares) is obtained.&#xA;(If it is desired) to transform a rectangle into a square (its breadth is taken as the side of a square and this square on the breadth is cut off from the rectangle), the remainder of the rectangle is divided into two (equal parts) and placed in its east and south side; (the empty space in the corner) is filled up by a (small extra) square piece. The removal of it (of the square piece from the square thus formed to get the required square) has been stated.&#xA;If (the rectangle be) very long, it should be cut again and again (into squares) making equal (the length to its) breadth; these squares are combined into one square; (to this is) added the (remaining) portion (of the rectangle) after transforming it suitably. This is the method of addition (ekaḥ samāsaḥ).&#xA;A square intended to be transformed into a rectangle is cut off by its diagonal (by drawing a line from its north-west corner to south-east corner); one portion (again is subdivided) into two equal parts and are added, one to its east and the other to the north; for a trapezium the side is cut off and added as it fits.&#xA;By unit measure the square unit is to be understood. On specific direction, it may be otherwise.&#xA;Square on a side of 2 units is 4; on 3 units it is 9 and on 4 units it is 16.&#xA;TRANSLATION&#xA;123&#xA;3.7&#xA;3.8&#xA;3.9&#xA;The number of units (in the side of a square) measured by a cord, when multiplied by the same, will give the total number of squares.&#xA;Half of the unit will produce its one-fourth, one-third its one-ninth, one- fourth its one-sixteenth.&#xA;This is (the method of) deduction (nirhāsa) which has been explained before. This is according to (the injunction) of the śāstra.&#xA;3.10 Enlargement (vivṛddhi) and deduction (hrāsa) are made, depending on the&#xA;unit of length in a cord (rajjupramāņa).&#xA;3.11&#xA;3.12&#xA;If it is desired to transform a square into a circle (a cord of length) half the diagonal (of the square) is stretched from the centre to the east (a part of it lying outside the eastern side of the square); with one-third (of the part lying outside) added to the remainder (of the half diagonal), the (required) circle is drawn. This gives the solution.&#xA;If it is desired to transform a circle into a square, its diameter is divided into fifteen parts and two of them are removed. The remaining (thirteen parts) will be the side (of the square).&#xA;4.1&#xA;4.2&#xA;4.3&#xA;4.4&#xA;The altar in the shape of a trough, chariot wheel, falcon, triangle, rhombus and a kind of pot in the shape of a wheel are the (citis of the corresponding) fire-altars.&#xA;For construction of trough (droṇacit) a square equal to seven-fold fire-altar together with its wings and tail (i.e., 71⁄2 sq. purușa) is drawn and the tenth part of the area (after being transformed into a square) is joined to the original square like a stalk. This is according to some (teacher). The original square (having an area of 7 sq. puruşa) is to be divided horizontally and vertically by drawing parallel lines from its tenth part; the (ten small squares) are then combined into a square (by the ekasamāsa method) and separated out. The remaining (squares are changed to a similar shape, i.e., a square). (Next) the previous part is to be joined to the latter (towards west like a stalk). The same (process) is adopted in the case of a circular (droṇacit).&#xA;In (the case of) an isosceles triangle (prauga) a square whose area is double the area of (the seven-fold) fire-altar with its wings and tail (i.e. 2×71=15 sq. puruşa) (is constructed) and a pole is put in the middle of the eastern side. This pole is then joined (by means of a cord) with poles at south-west and north-west corners. This gives (the construction for) the fire-altar.&#xA;In the case of rhombus (ubhayata prauga) a rectangle which has an area twice as much as in the seven-fold fire-altar together with its wings and tail, is con- structed and poles (are fixed) at the middle point of each of its sides. This will give the solution.&#xA;124&#xA;4.5&#xA;4.6&#xA;4.7&#xA;KATYAYANA-SULBASŪTRA&#xA;(Having desired) to transform an isosceles triangle (prauga) into a square, the former is divided by the prācī line, one (of its parts) is placed on the · opposite side after inverting it, and (the rectangle so formed) is transformed into a square by the (known) method of addition. This is the solution.&#xA;(Wishing to transform a rhombus into a square), it (the former) is bisected by its transverse middle line and recombined as before.&#xA;By this (method) the transformation of a triangle (into a square) is explained. This also explains the method of (constructing) a pentagon. A pentagon of equal angles is to be cut off into isosceles triangle and that having two types of angles into square.&#xA;5.1&#xA;5.2&#xA;5.3&#xA;5.4&#xA;5.5&#xA;5.6&#xA;5.7&#xA;5.8&#xA;5.9&#xA;5.10&#xA;5&#xA;How one hundred-and-one-fold fire-altar (from the original seven-fold fire- altar) is obtained gradually (by adding one square purușa) will be explained.&#xA;Two times, three times of the original fire-altar (which is 7 sq. purușa) is to be constructed always by the method of addition.&#xA;Upto twentyone-fold, the fire-altar is to be increased by the addition of one square purușa.&#xA;For (the purpose of) adding one (sq.) purușa to the original falcon-shaped fire-altar, a square equal (in area) to (that of) the original fire-altar with its wings and tail (i.e., 71⁄2 sq. purușa) is to be constructed and to it is added one (sq.) puruşa (by the method of samāsa.)&#xA;The original fire-altar is to be divided into fifteen equal parts. Two of these parts are to be transformed into a square (by the samāsa method. This will give the (new) unit (pramāņa) of the purușa.&#xA;One-fifth (of a purușa) is the measure for the bṛhatī brick and one-tenth (of a purușa) is for the padamātrā.&#xA;Or, an area of one square purușa is to be divided (into 25 parts) by (drawing) five lines both ways. Five of these small parts are to be transformed into a square, third part of which is cut off. The remaining (two parts) is added to one square purușa. This is another method (of determining the enlarged square unit).&#xA;One-fifteenth of a purușa is 8 añgulas.&#xA;5 aratnis, 10 vitastis, 120 añgulas are each equal to one purușa. One pada measures 12 añgulas.&#xA;Or, an area of one (sq.) puruşa is to be divided by seven (lines) drawn from both sides; seven (parts) of these are to be combined (into a square); from this combined sum, (a rectangle) of 14 añg. by 1 puruşa (to be transformed into a square) is to be subtracted (by the method of nirhāsa). The&#xA;TRANSLATION&#xA;125&#xA;5.11&#xA;remainder (which is a square) is added to one (sq.) purușa. This is another method.&#xA;By aratni and vitasti, no enlargement with (purușa) is to be understood; it is a number according to Śruti (i.e. enlargement of puruşa is to be made with its submultiple).&#xA;6.1&#xA;6.2&#xA;6.3&#xA;6.4&#xA;6.5&#xA;6.6&#xA;6.7&#xA;6.8&#xA;6.9&#xA;6&#xA;As the (area) of the fire-altar is increased, so is (increased) the unit of the bricks. This we will explain.&#xA;The side of a square of area 14 (square) prakramas will give the unit in prakrama for 101-fold fire-altar (construction above twentyone-fold).&#xA;Or, in the second and following construction, there should be an increase (of one square) prakrama for every seven constructions.&#xA;(At each successive construction), instead of the (original) prakrama the value of the prakrama should be enlarged by its one-seventh.&#xA;Such (seventh part increase) is continued upto 101-fold fire-altar.&#xA;There should be no increase in the antaḥpatya and the garhapatya agni. The yoni will remain (fixed), for, according to Śruti, (the number of) yoni never increases with the (number of the) birth. Accordingly, the increase of the yoni is prohibited.&#xA;The transverse (side) is to measure one less than the number of squares (of equal area) intended to be combined into a square; the two sides (together) should be one more than that; an (isosceles) triangle is to be formed (with the sides and the transverse side as the base); the altitude will produce it (the required square).&#xA;The increase of the altar depends on the distance between the poles (yupas). This we are going to explain.&#xA;The twentyfourth part of the cord measuring 11 paravān 10 akṣa (1172 ang.) of the chariot measure forms the (required) unit in prakrama.&#xA;6.10 Having constructed an altar with this unit (i.e. 1172 añg.), a (rectangular) portion of 12 angulas from the east of the altar is to be cut off, and then having considered the east-west line are placed the poles in the holes (made for this purpose).&#xA;6.11&#xA;Or, the half (of the holes used for the two end yūpas) at both sides should be inside the altar (and the other half outside). This is according to Śruti.&#xA;6.12 According to another (group of teachers), the first and the last pole (yupa)&#xA;should be placed inside the altar; this is natural.&#xA;6.13 It is an altar having a lock on the crown of the head (śikhaṇḍinī vedi).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>सर्व-प्रस्तुतिः</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/vAjasaneyam/sUtram/kAtyAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;रज्जुसमासं वक्ष्यामः १&lt;br&gt;&#xA;समे शङ्कुं निखाय शङ्कुसम्मितया&#xA;रज्ज्वा मण्ड-लं परिलिख्य यत्र लेखयोः शङ्क्वग्रच्छाया निपतति तत्र शङ्कू&#xA;निहन्ति सा प्राची । तदन्तरं रज्ज्वाभ्यस्य पाशौ कृत्वा शङ्क्वोः पाशौ&#xA;प्रतिमुच्य दक्षिणायम्य मध्ये शङ्कुमेवमुत्तरतः सोदीची २&lt;br&gt;&#xA;रज्ज्वन्तयोः&#xA;पाशौ करोति । श्रोण्यंसनिरञ्छनसङ्ख्यासमासभङ्गेषु लक्षणानि ।&#xA;प्राच्यन्त-योः शङ्कु निहन्ति । श्रोण्योरंसयोश्च ।&#xA;शङ्क्वोः पाशौ प्रतिमुच्य निरञ्छनेन गृहीत्वा दक्षिणपूर्वां दिशं&#xA;हरन्ति । एवमुत्तरतः । विपर्य-स्येतरतः । स समाधिः सर्वत्र ३&#xA;प्रमाणमभ्यस्याभ्यासचतुर्थे लक्ष्णं करोति&#xA;तन्निरञ्छनम् । अक्ष्णया तिर्यङ्मानीशेष ४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रमाणार्धं&#xA;वाभ्यस्या-भ्यासषष्ठे लक्षणं करोति तन्निरञ्छनम् ।&#xA;अक्ष्णया तिर्यङ्मानिशेषः ५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रमाणार्धे समचतुरश्रस्य शङ्कुः ।&#xA;शास्त्रवदर्धे दीर्घचतुरश्रस्य । शकट-मुखस्य चैवम् ६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एतेन&#xA;प्राग्वंशवेदिमानानि व्याख्यातानि । शाला-मानं च । तत्रोदीची प्राचीवत् ।&#xA;सदसश्चैवम् ७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अपरिमितं प्रमाणा-द्भूयः ८&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रमाणे शास्त्रं प्रमाणं&#xA;निर्हासविवृद्ध्योः । योगश्च ९&lt;br&gt;&#xA;इतरस्य-वितृतीये दक्षिणत&#xA;इत्येतद्वक्ष्यामः । गार्हपत्याहवनीययोरन्तरालं ष-ढ्धा सप्तधा वागन्तुसमं&#xA;त्रेधा विभज्यापरवितृतीयलक्षणेन दक्षिणायम्य तस्मिन्नग्निः ।&#xA;विपर्यस्योत्तरत उत्करः १०&#xA;अपिवान्तरत्रिभागोऽनया रज्ज्वा&#xA;पुर्वार्धे समचतुरश्रं कृत्वा श्रोण्यामग्निः ।&#xA;विपर्यस्योत्तरांस उत्करः ११&lt;br&gt;&#xA;१&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अङ्गुलै&#xA;रथसम्मितायाः प्रमाणम् । तत्राष्टाशीतिशतमीषा । चतुःशतम-क्षः ।&#xA;षडशीतिर्युगम् । चत्वारोऽष्टकाः शम्या १&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पैतृक्यां&#xA;द्विपुरुषं समचतुरश्रं कृत्वा करणीमध्ये शङ्कवः स समाधिः २&lt;br&gt;&#xA;करणी&#xA;तत्करणी तिर्यङ्मानी पार्श्वमान्यक्ष्णया चेति रज्जवः ३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पदं&#xA;तिर्यङ्मानी त्रिपदा पार्श्व-मानी तस्याक्ष्ण्या रज्जुर्दशकरणी ४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एवं&#xA;द्विपदा तिर्यङ्मानी षट्पदा पार्श्वमानी तस्याक्ष्णया&#xA;रज्जुश्चत्वारिंशत्करणी ५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;उपदिष्टं युगप्रमाणं&#xA;शम्याप्रमाणं च दर्शनात् ६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;दीर्घचतुरश्रस्याक्ष्णया रज्जुस्तिर्यङ्मानी&#xA;पार्श्वमानी च यत्पृथग्भूते कुरुतस्तदुभयं करोतीति क्षेत्रज्ञानम् ७&#xA;सम-चतुरश्रस्याक्ष्णया रज्जुर्द्विकरणी ८&lt;br&gt;&#xA;करणीं तृतीयेन&#xA;वर्धयेत्तच्च स्वचतुर्थेनात्मचतुस्तृंशोनेन सविशेष इति&#xA;विशेषः ९&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रमाणं तिर्यक् द्विकरण्यायामस्तस्याक्ष्णया&#xA;रज्जुस्त्रिकरणी १०&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तृतीयकरण्येतेन व्या-ख्याता ।&#xA;प्रमाणविभागस्तु नवधा करणीतृतीयं नवभागः ।&#xA;नवभा-गास्त्रयस्तृतीयकरणी ११&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सौत्रामण्यां&#xA;प्रक्रमार्था । तृतीयकरणी समा-सार्था १२&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तुल्यप्रमाणानां&#xA;समचतुरस्राणामुक्तः समासः । नाना-प्रमाणसमासे ह्रसीयसः करण्या&#xA;वर्षीयसोऽपच्छिन्द्यात्तस्याक्ष्णया रज्जुरुभे समस्यतीति समासः १३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;२&#xA;चतुरश्राच्चतुरश्रं&#xA;निर्जिहीर्षन्यावन्निर्जिहीर्षेत्तावदुभयतोऽपच्छिद्य&#xA;शङ्कू निखाय पार्श्वमानीं कृत्वा पार्श्वमानीसम्मितामक्ष्णयां तत्रोपसंहरति&#xA;स समासेऽपच्छेदः सा करण्येष निर्ह्रासः १&lt;br&gt;&#xA;दीर्घचतुरश्रं समचतुरश्रं&#xA;चिकीर्षन् मध्ये&#xA;तिर्यगपच्छिद्यान्यतरद्विभज्येतरत्पुरस्ताद्दक्षिणतश्चोपद-ध्याच्छेषमागन्तुना&#xA;पुरयेत्तस्योक्तो निर्ह्रासः २&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अतिदीर्घं&#xA;चेत्तिर्यङ्मा-न्यापच्छिद्यापच्छिद्यैकसमासेन&#xA;समस्य शेषं यथायोगमुपसंहरेदित्येकः समासः ३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;समचतुरश्रं दीर्घचतुरश्रं&#xA;चिकीर्षन्मध्येऽक्ष्णयाऽपच्छिद्य तच्च&#xA;विभज्यान्यतरत्पुरस्तादुत्तरतश्चोपदध्याद्विषमं&#xA;चेद्यथायोगमुपसंहरेदिति व्यासः ४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रमाणं चतुरश्रमादेशादन्यत् ५&#xA;द्विप्रमाणा चतुःकरणी त्रिप्र-माण नवकरणी&#xA;चतुःप्रमाणा षोडशकरणी ६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यावत्प्रमाणा रज्जुर्भवति&#xA;तावन्तस्तावन्तो वर्गा भवन्ति तान्समस्येत् ७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अर्धप्रमाणेन&#xA;पादप्रमाणं विधीयते । तृतीयेन नवमॐऽशः । चतुर्थेन&#xA;षोडशी कला ८&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एष निर्ह्रासस्तस्य पुरस्तादुक्तं शास्त्रम् ९&#xA;यावत्प्रमाणा रज्जुर्भवतीति विवृद्धे ह्रासो भवति १०&lt;br&gt;&#xA;चतुरश्रं&#xA;मण्डलं चिकीर्षन्मध्यादंसे निपात्य पार्श्वतः परिलिख्य तत्र यदतिरिक्तं&#xA;भवति तस्य तृतीयेन सह मण्डलं परिलिखेत् स समाधिः ११&lt;br&gt;&#xA;मण्डलं चतुरश्रं&#xA;चिकीर्षन् विष्कम्भं पञ्चदशभागान् कृत्वा द्वावुद्धरेच्छेषः करणी १२&#xA;३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;द्रोणचिद्रथचक्रचित्कङ्कचित्प्रौगचिदुभयतः प्रौगः समुह्यपुरीष&#xA;इत्य-ग्नयः १&lt;br&gt;&#xA;द्रोणे यावानग्निः&#xA;सपक्षपुच्छविशेषस्तावच्चतुरश्रं&#xA;कृत्वा द्रोणद-शमविभागो वृन्तमित्येके ।&#xA;तद्दशमेनापच्छिद्यापच्छिद्यैकसमासेन&#xA;समस्य निर्हृत्य सर्वमग्निं तथाकृतिं कृत्वा पुरस्तात्पश्चाद्वोपदध्यात् ।&#xA;मण्डलेऽप्येवम् २&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रौगे यावानग्निः सपक्षपुच्छविशेषस्तावद्द्विगुणं&#xA;चतुरश्रं कृत्वा यः पुरस्तात्करणीमध्ये शङ्कुर्यौ च श्रोण्योः&#xA;सोऽग्निः ३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;उभयतः प्रौगे तावदेव दीर्घचतुरश्रं कृत्वा करणीमध्येषु&#xA;शङ्कवः स समाधिः ४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रौगं चतुरश्रं चिकीर्षन्मध्ये प्राञ्चमपच्छिद्य&#xA;विपर्यस्येतरत उपधाय दीर्घचतुरश्रसमासेन समस्येत् स समाधिः ५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;उभयतः&#xA;प्रौगं चेन्मध्ये तिर्यगपच्छिद्य पूर्ववत्समस्येत् ६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एतेनैव&#xA;त्रिकर्णसमासो व्या-ख्यातः । पञ्चकर्णानां च ।&#xA;प्रौगेऽपच्छिद्यैककर्णानां ।&#xA;द्विकर्णानां समचतुरश्रेऽपच्छिद्य ७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;उत्तरेषु&#xA;पुरुषोच्चयेनैकशतविधादित्येतद्वक्ष्यामः&#xA;१&lt;br&gt;&#xA;आद्योऽग्निर्द्विगुण-स्त्रिगुणो भवतीति सर्वसमासः २&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एकविंशतिविधो भवतीति&#xA;पुरु-षाभ्यासः ३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पुरुषाभ्यासे यावानग्निः सपक्षपुच्छविशेषस्तावच्चतुरश्रं&#xA;कृत्वा तस्मिन्पुरुषप्रमाणमवदध्यात् ४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;समस्तं पञ्चदशभागान्कृत्वा&#xA;द्वावेकसमासेन समस्येत् स पुरुषः ५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पञ्चविभागेन बृहती&#xA;तस्य दश-मविभागेन पादमात्री भवति ६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पुरुषं वा पञ्चमेनोभयतोऽपच्छिद्य&#xA;पञ्च-विभागन्समस्य तृतीयं निर्हृत्य&#xA;तस्मिन्पुरुषप्रमाणेऽवदध्यादित्यपरम्&#xA;७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पञ्चदशविभागोऽष्टाङ्गुलम् ८&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पञ्चारत्निर्दशवितस्तिर्विंशतिशताङ्गुलः&#xA;पुरुष इत्येतस्माद्द्वादशाङ्गुलं पदमिति च ९&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पुरुषं वा&#xA;सप्तमेनोभयतो-ऽपच्छिद्य सप्तभागान्समस्य&#xA;ससप्तमभागमङ्गुलं निर्हृत्य&#xA;पुरुषप्रमाणे-ऽवदध्यादित्यपरम् १०&#xA;नारत्निवितस्तीनां समासो विद्यते सङ्ख्यायोगादिति श्रुतेः ११&#xA;५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यथाग्नि वेदीष्टकाप्रमाणं वर्द्धत इत्येतद्वक्ष्यामः १&lt;br&gt;&#xA;याकरणी&#xA;चतुर्दशप्र-क्रमान्सङ्क्षिपति त्रिंश्च&#xA;प्रक्रमसप्तमभागान् स एकशतविधे प्रक्रमः&#xA;२&lt;br&gt;&#xA;द्वितीये वा सप्तसु प्रक्रमेषु प्रक्रममवधाय तस्य सप्तमभागेन&#xA;प्रक्रमार्थः ३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;प्रक्रमेण वा सप्तमभागेन&#xA;प्रक्रमार्थः ४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एवमैकशतविधात् ५&#xA;नान्तःपात्यगार्हपत्ययोर्वृद्धिर्भवति&#xA;तावदेव योनिर्भवति न वै जातं गर्भं योनिरनुवर्धत इति&#xA;श्रुतेर्वृद्धेरत्यन्तं&#xA;प्रतिषेधः ६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यावत्प्रमाणानि समचतुरश्राण्येकीकर्तुं&#xA;चिकीर्षेदेकोनानि तानि भवन्ति तिर्यग्द्विगुणान्येकत&#xA;एकाधिकानि त्र्यस्रिर्भवति तस्येषुस्तत्करोति ७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यथायूपं&#xA;वेदिव-र्द्धनमित्येतद्वक्ष्यामः ८&lt;br&gt;&#xA;या&#xA;रज्जुरेकादशोपरवान्सङ्क्षिपति दश च रथा-क्षांस्तस्या यश्चतुर्विंशो भागः&#xA;स प्रक्रमः ९&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तेन वेदिं निर्माय द्वादशाङ्गुलं पुरस्तादपच्छिद्य&#xA;तद्यूपावत्याच्छङ्कोः पुरस्तात्प्राञ्चमवधाय तस्मिन्&#xA;यूपा-न्मिनोति १०&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पार्श्वयोर्वाऽर्धमन्तर्वेदीति&#xA;श्रुतेरर्द्धकानिति ११&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एके प्रथमोत्तमौ प्रकृतिवत् १२&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सैषा शिखण्डिनी वेदिः १३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;भवन्ति चात्र&#xA;श्लोकाः-द्विहस्ते लक्षणं कुर्यात् त्रिहस्तो मध्यमः शिरः १&#xA;शिरःपश्चाद्वितस्तिः स्यात् पूर्वार्धे हस्त एव च&#xA;सार्धहस्ते च पाशः स्यात् वेदिः स्यात् पौर्णमासिकी २&#xA;सङ्ख्याज्ञः परिमाणज्ञः समसूत्रनिरञ्छकः समभूमौ&#xA;भवेद्विद्वाञ्छुल्बवित् परिपृच्छकः ३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;न जलात्&#xA;सममन्यत् स्यान्नान्यद्वातात् प्रमा भवेत् नान्यद्दूरं भ्रमादूर्ध्वं&#xA;नान्यत् सूत्रादृजुर्भवेत् ४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तिर्यङ्मान्याश्च सर्वार्थैः&#xA;पार्श्वमान्याश्च योगवित् करणीनां विभागज्ञो&#xA;नित्योद्युक्तश्च कर्मसु ५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;शास्त्रबुध्या&#xA;विभागज्ञः परशास्त्रकुतूहलः शिल्पिभ्यः स्थपतिभ्यश्च&#xA;आददीत मतीः सदा ६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;षडङ्गुलपरीणाहं द्वादशाङ्गुलमुच्छ्रितम् जरठं&#xA;चाव्रणं चैव शङ्कुं कुर्याद्विशेषतः ७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;द्विवितस्तिप्रमाणस्तु&#xA;खादिरो मुद्गरस्तथा शङ्कुस्तेन निखातव्यस्तस्मात्तस्य परिग्रहः&#xA;८&lt;br&gt;&#xA;एकतस्तु ऋजुस्तीक्ष्णः खादिरः सममायतः शङ्कुः कार्यस्तु&#xA;शुल्बज्ञैस्तस्यार्धं गमयेन्महीम् ९&#xA;प्रादेशमात्रो हविर्यज्ञे पूर्वलक्षणलक्षितः शङ्कुरामशिराः&#xA;कार्यस्तस्याप्यर्धं निखापयेत् १०&lt;br&gt;&#xA;चतुरस्रमुद्गरं स्यात्&#xA;षोडशाङ्गुलमायतम् अविद्धं रमणीयं च दारुमध्याच्च निर्मितम् ११&#xA;अजीर्णाऽग्रन्थिनी सूक्ष्मा समा श्लक्ष्णा त्वरोमशा&#xA;रज्जुर्मानाधिका कार्या अध्वरे योगमिच्छता १२&lt;br&gt;&#xA;शाणी वा बाल्वजी&#xA;चैव वैणवी वा विधीयते रज्जुस्तूभयतःपाशा त्रिवृता यज्ञकर्मणि १३&#xA;रज्जुर्मुञ्जमयी कार्या शणैस्तु परिमिश्रिता कात्यायनो&#xA;वदत्येवमखण्डा कुशबल्बजैः १४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;नवके लक्षणं कुर्यात्&#xA;त्रीणि कुर्यात् त्रिषु त्रिषु उत्तमो नवकः पाशः सदसो मानमुच्यते&#xA;१५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पञ्चदशमथैकविंशतिकमपरं परस्त्रिकं च द्वादशसु पाश उत्तम इति सोमे&#xA;रज्जुमानमेतत् १६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पदस्याक्ष्णया तिरश्ची तयोरक्ष्णया भवेत्&#xA;सौत्रामण्यां विमातव्या वेदिः स्यात् सोमवत्तया १७&#xA;नीहारेण घनैर्वापि ज्योतिषामभ्रदर्शने अप्सु दीपं&#xA;प्रगृह्णीयाद्यावत्तमसि दर्शने १८&#xA;प्रमाणं च प्रमेयं च यच्चान्यद्वस्तुसञ्ज्ञकम् सर्वं&#xA;तच्छास्त्रतो ज्ञात्वा यज्ञे सिध्यन्ति याज्ञिकाः १९&#xA;यथा न क्षीयते मानं यथा च न विवर्धते यथा च रमते दृष्टिस्तथा योगं समाचरेत्&#xA;२०&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अरत्निश्चतुरस्रस्तु पूवस्याग्नेः खरो भवेत् रथचक्राकृतिः&#xA;पश्चाच्चन्द्रार्ध इव दक्षिणः २१&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अग्नीनां तु&#xA;खरः कार्यो मेखलात्रयसंयुतः द्वादशाङ्गुल उच्छ्राये विस्तारे चतुरङ्गुलः&#xA;२२&lt;br&gt;&#xA;तन्तुः पुष्करनालस्य षड्गुणः परिवेष्टितः वत्सतर्यास्त्रिहायण्या&#xA;बालेन सदृशो भवेत् २३&lt;br&gt;&#xA;त्रयस्त्रिहायणीबालाः सर्षपार्धं प्रचक्षते&#xA;द्विगुणं सर्षपं विद्याद्यवः पञ्च तु सर्षपाः २४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अङ्गुलस्य प्रमाणं तु&#xA;षड्यवाः पार्श्वसंस्थिताः&#xA;चतुर्विंशाङ्गुलोऽरत्निर्वितस्तिर्द्वादशाङ्गुला&#xA;२५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;व्यामस्यात्र प्रमाणं तु चतुर्न्यूनं शतं भवेत् पुरुषस्य प्रमाणं वै&#xA;विंशतिस्तु शताधिका २६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;हिरण्यशकलार्थे तु हिरण्यं यस्य नोच्यते&#xA;कृष्णलेनैव तद्व्याख्या यज्ञे सिध्यति याज्ञिकी २७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;कृष्णलं त्रियवं&#xA;मानं ताम्रायसमतः परम् सुवर्णादर्धं च माषाणां सुवर्णाश्च त्रिसप्ततिः २८&#xA;त्रीणि चैव सहस्राणि दद्याद्बहुसुवर्णके भूयः स्थपतितो ज्ञात्वा&#xA;सञ्ज्ञास्वन्यासु मानवित् स्वर्णकारो यथाऽभ्यासात्तथा भूयो&#xA;विवर्धते २९&lt;br&gt;&#xA;ह्रसते शोषपाकाभ्यां द्वात्रिंशद्भागमिष्टका&#xA;तस्मादार्द्रप्रमाणं तु कुर्यान्मानाधिकं बुधः ३०&#xA;अज्ञात्वा शुल्बसद्भावं यज्ञे सौत्रामणीसुते वेदिं ये कर्तुमिच्छन्ति&#xA;गिरिं भिन्दन्ति ते नखैः ३१&lt;br&gt;&#xA;दण्डरज्ज्वर्धमभ्यस्य षष्ठे त्वर्धस्य&#xA;लक्षणम् तथैव चेतरत्रापि तिर्यङ्मानं यदृच्छया ३२&lt;br&gt;&#xA;यावत्प्रमाणा रज्जुः&#xA;स्यात्तावानेवागमो भवेत् आगमार्धे भवेच्छङ्कुस्तदर्धे च निरञ्छनम् ३३&#xA;आधाने पदिकं कुर्यात् द्विपदः सौमिको भवेत् अग्नौ च त्रिपदं कुर्यात्&#xA;प्रक्रमं याज्ञिको बुधः ३४&lt;br&gt;&#xA;कृत्तिका श्रवणः&#xA;पुष्यश्चित्रास्वात्योर्यदन्तरम्&#xA;एतत्प्राच्या दिशो रूपं युगमात्रोदिते पुरः ३५&lt;br&gt;&#xA;पञ्चाशच्छर्कराः&#xA;पश्चात् पूर्वे देयास्त्रिसप्ततिः दक्षिणे तु प्रदातव्या दश&#xA;पञ्च च सप्त च ३६&lt;br&gt;&#xA;शंस्यश्चतुर्विंशतिपार्श्वभागश्चतुर्दशभिः&#xA;परिलेख्यस्तु नर्यम् तथैव&#xA;चाष्टद्विगुणैरथर्य्यस्त्रिंशद्भिरायम्य&#xA;हरेत्तृतीयम् ३७&lt;br&gt;&#xA;अग्नेरुदक्सार्धनवाङ्गुले मध्यं ततो लिखेत्&#xA;वृत्तमेकोनविंशत्या प्राचीज्या मध्यगा भवेत्&#xA;उदगर्धं विहायार्वाक् खराग्नेर्दक्षिणस्य तु ३८&lt;br&gt;&#xA;सूत्रदोषदरिद्रस्य&#xA;गूढमन्त्रस्य धीमतः समाप्तेयं क्रिया शौल्बी&#xA;कात्यायनमहात्मनः ३९&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
