<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;१ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;१ on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/01/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः विहारयोगान् व्याख्यास्यामः ॥ १.१ ॥
English We shall explain the methods of constructing (different) figures (on the ground for building sacrificial altars).
English - Comment CONSTRUCTION OF SQUARE, THE THEOREM OF SQUARE ON THE DIAGONAL AND THE VALUE OF \(sqrt{2}\)
Apastamba summarized the knowledge of geometry and related problems in the first three chapters. The first chapter deals with various methods of construction of square, the theorem of square on the diagonal of a square and rectangle, and the calculation of the value of \(sqrt{2}\) .</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/02/</guid>
      <description>English - comment CONSTRUCTION OF SQUARE, SURD, A SQUARE FROM A COMBINA- TION AND DIFFERENCE OF TWO SQUARES, AND TRANSFORMATION OF A RECTANGLE INTO A SQUARE
This chapter mainly deals with the methods of construction and transformation of geometrical figures like square and rectangle, already dealt by Baudhāyana.
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अथापरोयोगः ॥ २.१ ॥
English Now another method of construction (of a square).
मूलम् अथापरोयोगः ॥ २.१ ॥
टीका विहरणाविशेषः इत्यर्थः ॥</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shulbam/sarva-prastutiH/1/03/</guid>
      <description>English - comment TRANSFORMATION OF A SQUARE INTO A RECTANGLE AND A CIRCLE, OF A CIRCLE INTO A SQUARE, AND CONSTRUCTION AS WELL AS ENLARGEMENT OF SQUARES OF DIFFERENT MEASURES FOR SURFACE MEASUREMENTS
The chapter deals with the transformation of squares into rectangles and circles, and of circles into squares. The methods given are the same as those by Baudhāyana. Moreover, Āpastamba has given an idea of surface measures and methods of enlargement or construction of different squares.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
