<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 THE EXPLANATION OF THE PILING OF THE FIRE ALTAR on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 THE EXPLANATION OF THE PILING OF THE FIRE ALTAR on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Placing of the Fire in the Fire-pan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/1_The_Placing_of_the_Fire_in_the_Fire-pan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/1_The_Placing_of_the_Fire_in_the_Fire-pan/</guid>
      <description>01 He offers the Savitr offerings, for instigation. He offers with (an oblation) ladled up four times, cattle have four feet; verily he wins cattle; the quarters are four; verily he finds support in the quarters. The metres departed from the gods (saying), &amp;lsquo;We will not carry your oblation without sharing (in it)&amp;rsquo;; for them they kept this (oblation) ladled up four times, for the Puronuvakya the Yajya, the deity, the Vasat call; in that he offers what has been ladled up four times, he delights the metres, and they delighted carry to the gods his oblation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Preparation of the Ground for the Fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/2_The_Preparation_of_the_Ground_for_the_Fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/2_The_Preparation_of_the_Ground_for_the_Fire/</guid>
      <description>01 Headed by Visnu the gods won finally these worlds by the metres; in that he strides the strides of Visnu, the sacrificer becoming Visnu wins finally these worlds. &amp;lsquo;Thou art the step of Visnu, overcoming hostility&amp;rsquo;, he says; the earth is connected with the Gayatri, the atmosphere with the Tristubh, the sky with the Jagati, the quarters with the Anustubh; verily he wins in order these worlds with the metres.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Second and Later Layers of Bricks</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/3_The_Second_and_Later_Layers_of_Bricks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/3_The_Second_and_Later_Layers_of_Bricks/</guid>
      <description>01 Now this fire (ritual) is an extensive sacrifice; what part of it is performed or what not? The part of the sacrifice which is performed that is omitted becomes rotten; be puts down the Aśvin (bricks); the Aśvins are the physicians of the gods; verily by them be produces medicine for it. Five he puts down; the sacrifice is fivefold; verily he produces medicine for the whole extent of the sacrifice.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/4_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/4_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 The gods and the Asuras were in conflict, they could not decide the issue; Indra saw these bodies, he put them down; with them he conferred upon himself power, strength, and body; then the gods prospered, the Asuras were defeated. In that he puts down Indra&amp;rsquo;s bodies, the sacrificer with them bestows on himself power, strength, and body; verily also he piles up the fire with Indra and with a</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/5_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/5_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 In that he completes (the sacrifice) with one animal, (it is) for the continuity of the sacrifice and to avoid cutting it in two. The male animals belong to Indra; in that being Indra&amp;rsquo;s they are offered to the fires, he causes strife among the deities. He should use Tristubh verses, appertaining to Agni, for the Yajyas and Anuvakyas; in that they appertain to Agni, (the verses) are Agni&amp;rsquo;s, in that they are Tristubhs (they are) Indra&amp;rsquo;s; (verily they serve) for prosperity; he does not cause strife among the deities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/6_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/6_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 a Golden of colour, pure, purifying,
In which was born Kaśyapa, in which Indra,
They have conceived Agni as a germ, of varied forms; May these waters be gentle and kindly to us.
b Those in whose midst Varuna doth go,
Gazing on the truth and falsehood of men,
Dripping honey, pure, purifying;
May these waters be gentle and kindly to us.
c Those of which in the sky the gods make their food, Those that are in many places in the sky,</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/7_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/7_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 a &amp;lsquo;He who piles the fire without regard to the deity falls a victim to the deities; he becomes poorer; he who (piles it) according to the deity does not fall a victim to the deities; he becomes richer. With a Gayatri (verse) addressed to Agni should he stroke the first layer; with a Tristubh the second; with a Jagati the third; with an Anustubh the fourth; with a Pankti the fifth; verily he piles the fire according to the deity.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
