<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;सर्व-प्रस्तुतिः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;सर्व-प्रस्तुतिः on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>०१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/01/</guid>
      <description>English - comment In the first two chapters Baudhāyana has given a summary of geometrical knowledge and some results of mathematical interest required for the construction of sacrificial altars. How the knowledge was used in connection with the measuring of grounds and placing of different layers of bricks has been discussed in detail in subsequent chapters. This chapter deals specifically with the units of measurements of altars, methods of construction of squares and rectangles, application of surd numbers, and the theorem of square on the diagonal of a rectangle.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/02/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/02/</guid>
      <description>English - comment TRANSFORMATION OF GEOMETRICAL FIGURES
This chapter deals with the method of combination or difference of two separate squares into a square and the transformation of a square into a rectangle, an isosceles trapezium or a circle and vice versa.
CONSTRUCTION of a SQUARE BEING SUM OF, DIFFERENCE BETWEEN, TWO SQUARES
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः नानाचतुरश्रे समस्यन्कनीयसः करण्या वर्षीयसो वृध्रमुल्लिखेत् । वृध्रस्याक्ष्णयारज्जुः समस्तयोः पार्श्वमानी भवति १
English If it is desired to combine two squares of different measures, a (rectangular) part is cut off from the larger (square) with the side of the smaller; the diagonal of the cut-off (rectangular) part is the side of the combined square.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/03/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/03/</guid>
      <description>English - comment POSITIONS, RELATIVE DISTANCES AND AREAS OF SACRIFICIAL FIRES AND ALTARS
This and the following four chapters 4-7 deal with the positions, relative distances, and areas of various sacrificial fires and altars as also the types of bricks used in the construction of some of them. For a fuller appreciation of the details of mensuration presented by the śulbakāras in these chapters, a general idea regarding the plan of the sacrificial ground and the various fires and altars mentioned will be helpful.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/04/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/04/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः प्राग्वंशः षोडशप्रक्रमायामो द्वादशव्यासोऽपि वा द्वादशप्रक्रमायामो दशव्यासः १
English The sacrificial chamber (prāgvamsa) is 16 prakramas long by 12 prakramas broad, or else 12 prakramas long by 10 prakramas broad.
मूलम् प्राग्वंशः षोडशप्रक्रमायामो द्वादशव्यासोऽपि वा द्वादशप्रक्रमायामो दशव्यासः १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः तस्य मध्ये द्वादशिको विहारः २
English (A length of) 12 prakramas is left in the middle between the sacrificial fires.
मूलम् तस्य मध्ये द्वादशिको विहारः २
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः त्रिंशत्पदानि प्रक्रमा वा पश्चात्तिरश्ची भवति षट्त्रिंशत्प्राची चतुर्विंशतिः पुरस्तात्तिरश्चीति महावेदेर्विज्ञायते । मानयोगस्तस्या व्याख्यातः । आहवनीयात्षट् प्रक्रमान्महावेदिः ३</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/05/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/05/</guid>
      <description>English - comment ENLARGEMENT OF FIRE-ALTAR FROM \(7\frac{1}{2}\) SQ. PURUṢAS TO \(101\frac{1}{2}\) SQ. PURUSAS, HEIGHT OF ALTARS AND THEIR PECULIARITIES
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अर्धाष्टमाः पुरुषाः प्रथमोऽग्निः । अर्धनवमा द्वितीयः । अर्धदशमास्तृतीयः । एवमुत्तरोत्तरो विधाभ्यास एकशतविधात् । तदेतत्सप्तविध-प्रभृत्येकशतविधान्तम् १
English The area of the fire-altar made for the first time is \(1\frac{1}{2}\) square purușa; that for the second time \(8\frac{1}{2}\) (square purușa); that for the third time \(9\frac{1}{2}\) (square puruṣa). Thus by successively adding one-fold (1 square purușa), (one can go) upto 101-fold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/06/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/06/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः पशुधर्मो ह वा अग्निः । यथा ह वै पशोर्दक्षिणेषामस्थ्नां यद्दक्षिणं पार्श्वं तदुत्तरेषामुत्तरं यदुत्तरेषां दक्षिणं तद्दक्षिणेषामुत्तरं यदवाक् चोर्ध्वं च तत्समानमेवमिष्टकानां रूपाण्युपदध्यात् १
English The fire-altar indeed possesses the characteristics of an animal. The southern bones of an animal are on its southern (right) side; likewise its northern bones lie on its northern (left) side and vice versa. That (part) which is below (on the western side) is the same as what is above (on the eastern side).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/07/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/07/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः न खण्डामुपदध्यात् । न भिन्नामुपदध्यात् । न कृष्णामुपदध्यात् । न जीर्णामुपदध्यात् । न लक्ष्मणामुपदध्यात् । न स्वयमातृण्णां स्वयञ्चितावुपदध्यात् १
English One should not use (for the laying of the fire-altar) a broken brick, a brick which is cleft, a blackened brick (due to over or under heating), a damaged brick and a brick with scratching marks. In the layer where a brick full of natural holes (svayamātṛṇṇa) is used it is not to be covered (by a brick).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/08/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/08/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अथ वै भवति श्येनचितं चिन्वीत सुवर्गकाम इति १
English Now he who desires heaven is to construct a fire-altar in the form of a falcon.
मूलम् अथ वै भवति श्येनचितं चिन्वीत सुवर्गकाम इति १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः आकृतिद्वैविध्यम् । चतुराश्रात्मा श्येनाकृतिश्च २
English It is of two different forms; one has its body in the form of a square and the other in the form of a falcon.
मूलम् आकृतिद्वैविध्यम् । चतुराश्रात्मा श्येनाकृतिश्च २</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>०९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/09/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/09/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अथापरः १
English Now another type (of square fyenacit).
मूलम् अथापरः १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः पुरुषस्य पञ्चम्यः । ता एवैकतोऽध्यर्धाः । तासामर्ध्याः पाद्याश्च २
English (For this are required bricks of side equal to) one-fifth (pañcami) of a purușa; (those) with one side longer by half (adhyardha) of one-fifth (of a purușa); (these equal to) a half of its size (ardhyā of the pañcami); and (those equal to) a quarter of its size (pādyā of the pañcami).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/10/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/10/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अथ वक्रपक्षो व्यस्तपुच्छः १
English Now (is described the construction of a fire-altar in the form of a falcon) with curved wings and extended tail.
English - comment CONSTRUCTION OF A FIRE-ALTAR IN THE FORM OF A FALCON WITH CURVED WINGS AND EXTENDED TAIL-FIRST TYPE.
10.1. This type of fire-altar is constructed more in the likeness of a falcon. To achieve this the two wings are to be curved or bent and the tail is to be extended, that is, spread out.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>११</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/11/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/11/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अथापरः १
English Now another type (of falcon-shaped fire-altar with curved wings and extended tail).
मूलम् अथापरः १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः पुरुषस्य पञ्चमीभिः शतमशीतिः सप्तार्धं च सारत्निप्रादेशः सप्तविधः सम्पद्यते २
English (In this case) the seven-fold (fire-altar) with (two) aratnis and (one) prādeśa is accomplished with \(187\frac{1}{2}\) (square bricks) of side equal to one-fifth of a puruşa (pañcamī).
मूलम् पुरुषस्य पञ्चमीभिः शतमशीतिः सप्तार्धं च सारत्निप्रादेशः सप्तविधः सम्पद्यते २
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः तासां पञ्चाशद्द्वे चात्मन्यर्धचतुर्थ्यः शिरसि । पञ्चदश पुच्छे । अष्टपञ्चाशत्सार्ध्या दक्षिणे पक्ष उपदध्यात् । तथोत्तरे ३</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१२</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/12/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः कङ्कचित एतेनात्मा पुच्छं च व्याख्यातम् १
English The body and the tail of the kite-shaped fire-altar (kaṅkacit) are explained in the same manner (as those of the śyenacit just described).
मूलम् कङ्कचित एतेनात्मा पुच्छं च व्याख्यातम् १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः शिरसि पञ्चोपदध्यात् । तस्याकृतिर्व्याख्यात २
English 5 (pañcami) bricks are to be accommodated in the head whose shape has been explained.
मूलम् शिरसि पञ्चोपदध्यात् । तस्याकृतिर्व्याख्यात २
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः सप्तपञ्चाशद्दक्षिणे पक्ष उपदध्यात् । तथोत्तरे ३</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१३</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/13/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अलजचित एतेनात्मा शिरः पुच्छं च व्याख्यातं पादावपोद्धृत्य १
English The body, the head and the tail of the fire-altar in the form of an alaja bird are explained in the same manner (as those of the kaǹkacit) with the two feet withdrawn.
मूलम् अलजचित एतेनात्मा शिरः पुच्छं च व्याख्यातं पादावपोद्धृत्य १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः त्रिषष्टिर्दक्षिणे पक्ष उपदध्यात् । तथोत्तरे २
English 63 (pañcami) bricks are to be accommodated in the southern wing and the same in the northern.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१४</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/14/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/14/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः प्रौगचितं चिन्वीतेति १
English A fire-altar in the form of an isosceles triangle (prauga) is to be constructed as follows.
मूलम् प्रौगचितं चिन्वीतेति १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः यावानग्निः सारत्निप्रादेशस्तावत्प्रौगं कृत्वा तस्यापरस्याः करण्या द्वादशेनेष्टकास्तदर्धव्यासाः कारयेत् । तासामर्ध्याः पाद्याश्च २
English An isosceles triangle equal in area to the (seven-fold) fire-altar with (two) aratnis and (one) pradeśa (that is, 7 sq. purușa) is laid. Bricks (called bṛhati) of length equal to one-twelfth of its western side and breadth equal to half (of the length) are to be made; then bricks which are half and quarter (of the bṛhatīs).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१५</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/15/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/15/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः उभयतः प्रौगं चिन्वीतेति १
English A fire-altar in the form of a rhombus (made of two isosceles triangles, (ubhayata prauga) is to be constructed as follows.
मूलम् उभयतः प्रौगं चिन्वीतेति १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः यावानग्निः सारत्निप्रादेशस्तावदुभयतः प्रौगं कृत्वा नवमेन तिर्यङ्मान्याः प्रौगचितोक्ता विकाराः २
English A rhombus equal in area to the (seven-fold) fire-altar with (two) aratnis and (one) prādesa (that is, \(1\frac{1}{2}\) sq. puruṣa) is laid. As in the case of fire-altar in the form of isosceles triangle, bricks and their variations are to be made with the ninth part of the breadth (of the rectangle used for the construction of the rhombus).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१६</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/16/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/16/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः रथचक्रचितं चिन्वीतेति विज्ञायते १
English According to tradition, a fire-altar in the form of a chariot wheel is to be constructed.
मूलम् रथचक्रचितं चिन्वीतेति विज्ञायते १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः द्वयानि तु खलु रथचक्राणि भवन्ति साराणि च प्रधियुक्तानि च । अविशेषात्ते मन्यामहेऽन्यतरस्याकृतिरिति २
English The chariot wheels are indeed of two types, e.g. those with spokes and those (formed) by the joining of circular segments (to a central square piece). In the absence of any distinction between the two, both are taken into consi- deration and described.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१७</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/17/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/17/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः द्रोणचितं चिन्वीतेति विज्ञायते १
English According to tradition, a fire-altar in the form of a trough is to be constructed.
मूलम् द्रोणचितं चिन्वीतेति विज्ञायते १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः द्वयानि तु खलु द्रोणानि भवन्ति चतुरश्राणि च परिमण्डलानि च । अविशेषात्ते मन्यामहेऽन्यतरस्याकृतिरिति २
English The troughs are indeed of two types, e.g. the square-shaped and the circular. In the absence of any distinction between the two, both are taken into consideration and described.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१८</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/18/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/18/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अथापरः १
English Now the other type (of dronacit in the form of a circle).
मूलम् अथापरः १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः पुरुषस्य षोडशीभिर्विंशशतं सारत्निप्रादेशः सप्तविधः सम्पद्यते २
English 120 (square) bricks, each \(\frac{1}{16}\) of a (square) puruṣa (ṣoḍaśī, side\(=\frac{1}{4}\) pu. or 30 aṅg.) give the area of the seven-fold (fire-altar of \(7\frac{1}{2}\) sq. purușa) with (two) aratnis and (one) prādeśa.
मूलम् पुरुषस्य षोडशीभिर्विंशशतं सारत्निप्रादेशः सप्तविधः सम्पद्यते २
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः तासामेकामपोद्धृत्य शेषाः परिमण्डलं करोति ३</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>१९</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/19/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/19/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः श्मशानचितं चिन्वीतेति विज्ञायते १
English According to tradition, a fire-altar in the form of a pyre (śmaśānacit) is to be constructed.
मूलम् श्मशानचितं चिन्वीतेति विज्ञायते १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः सर्वमग्निं चतुरश्रान्पञ्चदश भागा-न्कृत्वा तेषामाख्यातमुपधानम् २
English The entire (area of the) fire-altar is divided into 15 square-parts. How to do this has been stated.
English THE CONSTRUCTION OF FIRE-ALTARS IN THE FORM OF A PYRE (ŚMAŚĀNACIT).
19.1-19.2. The fire-altar in the form of a pyre, as we shall presently see, is a trapezium.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२०</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/20/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/20/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः कूर्मचितं चिन्वीत यः कामयेत ब्रह्मलोकमभिजयेयमिति । विज्ञायते १
English According to tradition, a fire-altar in the form of a tortoise (kūrmacit) is to be constructed by one desiring to win the world of the Supreme Spirit (Brahmaloka).
मूलम् कूर्मचितं चिन्वीत यः कामयेत ब्रह्मलोकमभिजयेयमिति । विज्ञायते १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः द्वयाः खलु कूर्मा भवन्ति वक्राङ्गाश्च परिमण्डलाश्च । अविशेषात्ते मन्यामहेऽन्यतरस्याकृतिरिति २
English The tortoises are indeed of two types, e.g. those with twisted limbs and those with rounded ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>२१</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/21/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/baudhAyanaH/shulba-sUtrANi/sarva-prastutiH/21/</guid>
      <description>विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः अथापरः १
English Now the other type (of kūrmacit with rounded limbs).
मूलम् अथापरः १
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः पुरुषस्य षोडशीभिर्विंशशतं सारत्निप्रादेशः सप्तविधः सम्पद्यते २
English 120 (square) bricks of side equal to \(\frac{1}{16}\) purușa (ṣoḍaśī) give the area of the seven-fold (fire-altar of \(7\frac{1}{2}\) sq. purușa) with (two) aratnis and (one) prādeśa).
मूलम् पुरुषस्य षोडशीभिर्विंशशतं सारत्निप्रादेशः सप्तविधः सम्पद्यते २
विश्वास-प्रस्तुतिः तासां पञ्च षोडशीरपोद्धृत्य शेषाः परिमण्डलं करोति । तदुत्तरेण द्रोणचिता व्याख्यातम् ३</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
