<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;6 THE EXPLANATION OF THE SOMA SACRIFICE on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;6 THE EXPLANATION OF THE SOMA SACRIFICE on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifce</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/1_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/1_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifce/</guid>
      <description>01 He makes a hall with beams pointing east. The gods and men divided the quarters, the gods (obtained) the eastern, the Pitrs the southern, men the western, the Rudras the northern. In that he makes a hall with beams pointing east, the sacrificer approaches the world of the gods. He covers it over, for the world of the gods is hidden from the world of men. &amp;lsquo;It is not easy&amp;rsquo;, they say, &amp;rsquo;to go from this world; for who knows if he is in yonder world or not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/2_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/2_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 If he should offer hospitality after unyoking both (the oxen), he would break up the sacrifice. If (he should offer) before he has unyoked both, it would be as when hospitality is offered to one who has
not yet arrived. One ox is unyoked, one ox is not unyoked; then he offers hospitality, for the continuance of the sacrifice. The wife (of the sacrificer) holds on (to the cart); for the wife is mistress of the household gear; verily he offers what is approved by the wife.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/3_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/3_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 From the pit he scatters (earth) on the altars; the pit is the birthplace of the sacrifice; (verily it serves) to unite the sacrifice with its birthplace. The gods lost by conquest the sacrifice; they won it again from the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar; the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar is the invincible part of the sacrifice. In that he draws off the altar fires from that of the Agnidh, he renews the sacrifice from the invincible part of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Exposition Of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/4_The_Exposition_Of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/4_The_Exposition_Of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 By means of the sacrifice Prajapati created offspring; verily he created them by the subsidiary sacrifices; in that he offers the subsidiary sacrifices, verily thus the sacrificer creates offspring. He cuts off from the hind portion, for from the hind portion offspring are born; he cuts off from the thick side, for offspring are born from the thick side; he cuts off without confusion, to prevent confusion of the vital airs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 The Exposition of the Soma Sacrifice (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/5_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/5_The_Exposition_of_the_Soma_Sacrifice_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 Indra raised his bolt to hurl at Vrtra; Vrtra was afraid of the bolt when raised to be hurled; he said, &amp;lsquo;Hurl it not at me; there is this strength in me, that will I bestow on thee&amp;rsquo;; on him he bestowed the Ukthya. At him he raised (the bolt) to hurl a second time; he said, &amp;lsquo;Hurl it not at me; there is this strength in me, that will I bestow on thee&amp;rsquo; [1]; on him he bestowed again the Ukthya.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6 The Exposition of the Daksina and other Offerings</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/6_The_Exposition_of_the_Daksina_and_other_Offerings/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/6_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE/6_The_Exposition_of_the_Daksina_and_other_Offerings/</guid>
      <description>01 The sacrifices with the gifts are offered for the world of heaven. He offers with two (verses) on the Garhapatya; the sacrificer has two feet; (verily it serves) for support. He offers in the Agnidh&amp;rsquo;s altar; verily he ascends the atmosphere. He approaches the Sadas; verily he makes him go to the world of heaven. He offers in the Garhapatya with verses addressed to Surya; verily he makes him mount</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
