<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;5 THE EXPLANATION OF THE PILING OF THE FIRE ALTAR on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;5 THE EXPLANATION OF THE PILING OF THE FIRE ALTAR on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The Placing of the Fire in the Fire-pan</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/1_The_Placing_of_the_Fire_in_the_Fire-pan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/1_The_Placing_of_the_Fire_in_the_Fire-pan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;He offers the Savitr offerings, for instigation. He offers with (an oblation) ladled up four times, cattle have four feet; verily he wins cattle; the quarters are four; verily he finds support in the quarters. The metres departed from the gods (saying), &amp;lsquo;We will not carry your oblation without sharing (in it)&amp;rsquo;; for them they kept this (oblation) ladled up four times, for the Puronuvakya the Yajya, the deity, the Vasat call; in that he offers what has been ladled up four times, he delights the metres, and they delighted carry to the gods his oblation. If he desire of a man [1], &amp;lsquo;May he become worse&amp;rsquo;, he should offer each separately for him; verily he makes him severed from the libations; he becomes worse. If he desire of a man, &amp;lsquo;May he become better&amp;rsquo;, he should offer all for him continuously; verily he makes him master of the libation; he becomes better. This is the mastering of the sacrifice. He abandons prosperity in the beginning of the sacrifice who departs from Agni as the deity; these offerings to Savitr number eight, the Gayatri has eight syllables, Agni is connected with the Gayatri [2]; verily he does not abandon prosperity at the beginning of the sacrifice, nor Agni as the deity. The offerings to Savitr number eight, the libation (as a whole) is the ninth; verily he extends the threefold (Stoma) at the beginning of the sacrifice. If he desire, &amp;lsquo;May I confer on the metres the glory of the sacrifice&amp;rsquo;, he should make a Re verse last; verily he confers on the metres the glory of the sacrifice. If he desire, &amp;lsquo;May I confer on the sacrificer the glory of the sacrifice&amp;rsquo;, he should make a Yajus formula last; verily he confers on the sacrificer the glory of the sacrifice. &amp;lsquo;By the Rc make the Stoma to flourish&amp;rsquo;, he says [3], for prosperity. With four (verses) he takes up the spade; the metres are four; verily (he takes it up) with the metres. &amp;lsquo;On the instigation of god Savitr&amp;rsquo;, he says, for instigation. Agni went away from the gods, he entered the reed; he resorted to the hole which is formed by the perforation of the reed; the spade is perforated to make it his birthplace; wherever he lived, that became black; (the spade) is stained, for perfection of form; it is pointed at both ends, for the winning of light both hence and from yonder world; it is a fathom long; so much is the strength in man; (verily it is) commensurate with his strength; it is unlimited in girth, to win what is unlimited; that tree which has fruit is strong among trees, the reed bears fruit, (the spade) is of reed, to win strength.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2 The Preparation of the Ground for the Fire</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/2_The_Preparation_of_the_Ground_for_the_Fire/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/2_The_Preparation_of_the_Ground_for_the_Fire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Headed by Visnu the gods won finally these worlds by the metres; in that he strides the strides of Visnu, the sacrificer becoming Visnu wins finally these worlds. &amp;lsquo;Thou art the step of Visnu, overcoming hostility&amp;rsquo;, he says; the earth is connected with the Gayatri, the atmosphere with the Tristubh, the sky with the Jagati, the quarters with the Anustubh; verily he wins in order these worlds with the metres. Prajapati created Agni; he being created went away from him [1]; he followed him with this (verse), &amp;lsquo;He hath cried&amp;rsquo;; with it he won the home dear to Agni; in that he repeats this (verse), he wins thereby the home dear to Agni. Now he who steps the strides of Visnu is apt as he goes away to be burnt up; he turns with four (verses); the. metres are four, Agni&amp;rsquo;s dear body is the metres; verily he turns round on his dear body [2]; he turns round from left to right; verily he turns round on his own strength; therefore the right side of the body is the stronger; verily also does he turn with the turning of the sun. Varuna seized Śunahśepa Ajigarti, he saw this verse addressed to Varuna, by it he freed himself from the noose of Varuna; Varuna seizes him who takes the fire-pan; &amp;lsquo;From us the highest knot, O Varuna&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily thereby he frees himself from Varuna&amp;rsquo;s noose [3]. &amp;lsquo;I have drawn thee&amp;rsquo;, he says, for he draws him. &amp;lsquo;Be thou firm and motionless&amp;rsquo;, he says, for support. &amp;lsquo;Let all the folk desire thee&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily with the folk he unites him. &amp;lsquo;In him establish the kingdom&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily in him he makes the kingdom to abide. If he desire of a man, &amp;lsquo;May he be a ruler&amp;rsquo;, he should think of him with his mind; verily he becomes a ruler [4]. &amp;lsquo;In greatness he hath risen erect in the van of the dawns&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he makes him the first of his peers. &amp;lsquo;Emerging from the darkness&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he smites away darkness from him. &amp;lsquo;He hath come with the light&amp;rsquo;, he says; verily he bestows light upon him. He places him with four (verses); the metres are four; verily with the metres (he places him); with an Atichandas as the last; the Atichandas is the highest of metres; verily he makes him the highest of his peers; it contains [5] the word &amp;lsquo;sit&amp;rsquo; (sad); verily he makes him attain reality (sat-tvám). With (the hymn) of Vatsapri he reverences (him); by that did Vatsapri Bhalandana win the home dear to Agni; verily by it he wins the home dear to Agni. It has eleven (verses); verily in eleven places he bestows strength on the sacrificer. By the Stoma the gods prospered in this world, by the metres in yonder world; the hymn of Vatsapri is the type of the Stoma; in that he pays reverence with (the hymn) of Vatsapri [6], he wins with it this world; in that he strides the steps of Visnu, he wins by them yonder world. On the first day he strides forth, on the next day he pays reverence; therefore the minds of some creatures are set on energy, those of others on rest; therefore the active lords it over him who takes his ease therefore the active fixes upon a man who takes his ease. He clenches his fist, he restrains his speech, for support.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3 The Second and Later Layers of Bricks</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/3_The_Second_and_Later_Layers_of_Bricks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/3_The_Second_and_Later_Layers_of_Bricks/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Now this fire (ritual) is an extensive sacrifice; what part of it is performed or what not? The part of the sacrifice which is performed that is omitted becomes rotten; be puts down the Aśvin (bricks); the Aśvins are the physicians of the gods; verily by them be produces medicine for it. Five he puts down; the sacrifice is fivefold; verily he produces medicine for the whole extent of the sacrifice. He puts down the seasonal (bricks), to arrange the seasons [1]. Five he puts down; the seasons are five; verily he arranges the seasons in their whole number. They begin and end alike; therefore the seasons are alike; they differ in one foot; therefore the seasons differ likewise. He puts down the breath-supporters; verily he places the breaths in the months; therefore being alike the seasons do not grow old; moreover he generates them. The breath is the wind; in that having put down the seasonal (bricks) he puts down the breath-sup porters [2], therefore the wind accompanies all the seasons. He puts down the rain-winners; verily he wins rain. If he were to put them down in one place, then would fall rain in one season only; he puts them down after carrying them round in order; therefore it rains in all the seasons. Since having put down the breath-supporters he puts down the rain-winners, therefore the rain starts from the sky, impelled downwards by the wind. The strengthening (bricks) are cattle; cattle have various purposes and various customs, but only as regards water are they of one purpose [3]; if he desire of a man, &amp;lsquo;May he be without cattle&amp;rsquo;, he should put down for him the strengthening (bricks) and then put down the water (bricks); verily he makes discord for him with cattle; verily he becomes without cattle. If he desire of a man, &amp;lsquo;May he possess cattle&amp;rsquo;, he should put down for him the water (bricks) and then put down the strengthening (bricks); verily he makes concord for him with cattle and he becomes possessed of cattle. He puts down four in front; therefore the eye has four forms, two white, two black [4]. The (verses) contain the word &amp;lsquo;head&amp;rsquo;; therefore the head (of the fire) is in front. Five he puts down in the right hip, five in the left; therefore the animal is broader behind and receding in front; &amp;lsquo;The goat in strength&amp;rsquo;, (with these words he puts down) on the right shoulder; (with) &amp;lsquo;The ram in strength&amp;rsquo;, on the left; verily he puts together the shoulders (of the fire). &amp;lsquo;The tiger in strength&amp;rsquo;, (with these words) he puts down in the right wing, (with) &amp;lsquo;The lion in strength&amp;rsquo; on the left; verily he gives strength to the wings. (With) &amp;lsquo;The man in strength&amp;rsquo; (he puts down) in the middle; therefore man is overlord of animals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/4_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/4_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The gods and the Asuras were in conflict, they could not decide the issue; Indra saw these bodies, he put them down; with them he conferred upon himself power, strength, and body; then the gods prospered, the Asuras were defeated. In that he puts down Indra&amp;rsquo;s bodies, the sacrificer with them bestows on himself power, strength, and body; verily also he piles up the fire with Indra and with a&lt;br&gt;&#xA;body; be prospers himself, his foe is [1] defeated. The sacrifice departed from the gods; they could not recover it; they saw these bodies of the sacrifice, they put them down, and by them they recovered the sacrifice. In that he puts down the bodies of the sacrifice, the sacrificer by them wins the sacrifice. Three and thirty he puts down; the gods are three and thirty; verily he wins the gods; verily also he piles up the fire with itself and with a body; he becomes with his body in yonder world [2], who knows thus. He puts down the lighted (bricks); verily he confers light upon it; the fire blazes piled up with these (bricks); verily with them he kindles it; in both worlds is there light for him. He puts down the constellation bricks; these are the lights of the sky; verily he wins them;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/5_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/5_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In that he completes (the sacrifice) with one animal, (it is) for the continuity of the sacrifice and to avoid cutting it in two. The male animals belong to Indra; in that being Indra&amp;rsquo;s they are offered to the fires, he causes strife among the deities. He should use Tristubh verses, appertaining to Agni, for the Yajyas and Anuvakyas; in that they appertain to Agni, (the verses) are Agni&amp;rsquo;s, in that they are Tristubhs (they are) Indra&amp;rsquo;s; (verily they serve) for prosperity; he does not cause strife among the deities. To Vayu of the team he offers a hornless (animal); Vayu is the brilliance of Agni; it is offered to brilliance; therefore wheresoever the wind [1] blows, the fire burns; verily it follows its own brilliance. If he were not to offer to him of the team, the sacrificer would go mad; (an offering) is made to him of the team, to prevent the sacrificer going mad. The Yajya and the Anuvakya, contain (the words) &amp;lsquo;wind&amp;rsquo; and &amp;lsquo;white&amp;rsquo;, to secure brilliance. &amp;lsquo;The golden germ first arose&amp;rsquo;, (with these words) he pours out the butter portion; the golden germ is Prajapati; (verily it serves) for likeness to Prajapati. This (animal) is slain to make up all forms of animals; its hairs are [2] the form of man, its lack of horns that of horses, the possession of one set of incisors only that of cows, the sheep-like&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>6 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/6_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/6_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a&#34;&gt;a&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Golden of colour, pure, purifying,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;In which was born Kaśyapa, in which Indra,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;They have conceived Agni as a germ, of varied forms; May these waters be gentle and kindly to us.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;b&#34;&gt;b&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those in whose midst Varuna doth go,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Gazing on the truth and falsehood of men,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Dripping honey, pure, purifying;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;May these waters be gentle and kindly to us.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;c&#34;&gt;c&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Those of which in the sky the gods make their food, Those that are in many places in the sky,&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Those that inundate the earth with their sap [1], the pure ones May these waters be gentle and kindly to us.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>7 The Piling of the Fire Altar (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/7_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sArasvata-vibhAgaH/saMhitA/keith/5_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_PILING_OF_THE_FIRE_ALTAR/7_The_Piling_of_the_Fire_Altar_continued/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;01&#34;&gt;01&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;a&#34;&gt;a&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&amp;lsquo;He who piles the fire without regard to the deity falls a victim to the deities; he becomes poorer; he who (piles it) according to the deity does not fall a victim to the deities; he becomes richer. With a Gayatri (verse) addressed to Agni should he stroke the first layer; with a Tristubh the second; with a Jagati the third; with an Anustubh the fourth; with a Pankti the fifth; verily he piles the fire according to the deity. He falls not a victim to the deities; he becomes richer. This is the dividing of the sacrificial food; the food is cattle, and he piles it with cattle [1].&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
