<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;Introduction on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;Introduction on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>01 Śrautasūtras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/01_shrautasUtras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/01_shrautasUtras/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The Śrautasūtras are an important part of the Kalpa Vedānga. They deal with the ritual called Śrauta for which the performer must be an āhitāgni (i.e, one who has established the three sacred fires). An āhitāgni is basically a married man belonging to one of the three classes viz. Brāhmaṇa, Ksatriya or Vaiśya. When a man belonging to one of these classés gets married it becomes obligatory on his part to worship the fire in the presence of which he got married. This fire is called grhya (domestic) fire. The married man (gr̥hastha) maintains the domestic fire and performs all the domestic ritual in that fire. If he is rich and capable enough, he may like to establish the Śrauta-fires and then perform the Śrauta-ritual. The Śrauta fires are called Gārhapatya, Āhavanīya and Dakṣiṇa. The Śrautasūtras describes the Śrauta-ritual. Each one of the Śrautasūtras belongs to a particular Veda. They describes the duties of the priests belonging to that Veda in particular, but occasionally refer to the duties of the other priests also. To the R̥gveda belong following priests: Hotr̥, Maitrāvaruṇa, Acchāvāka, Grāvastut; to the Yajurveda: Adhvaryu, Pratipra sthāts, Neṣṭr̥, Unnets; to the Sāmaveda: Udgātr̥, Prastotr̥, Subrahmaṇya, Pratihartr̥; and to the Atharvaveda: Brahman, Brāhmaṇācchaṁsin, Potr̥, Āgnīdhra.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>02 Śrauta rituals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/02_shrauta_rituals/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/02_shrauta_rituals/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(2) The Śrauta-rituals are mainly of two types: i) Havir yajñas (Iṣṭis) and ii) Somayajñas. The New and Full-moon sacrifies (Darsapūrṇamāsau) form the basic paradigm of the Havir-yajñas. Agnistoma forms the basic paradigm of the Soma Sacrifices. The Somayajñas are divided into three categories which are based upon the duration of the performance as well as peculiarities of the performance as such: i) Ekāha one-day sacrifices; ii) Ahīna: sacrifices being performed for two to twelve days iii) Sattra: Sacrifices being performed for twelve days or more number of days. The longest sacrifices mentioned by the ritual texts are to be performed for one thousand years.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>03 Śrautasūtra list</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/03_shrautasUtra_list/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/03_shrautasUtra_list/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(3) The Veda has different branches (sākhās) and accor dingly there are different Śrautasūtras belonging to different vedic branches. It is well-known that may branches are now known only through the names and the literature belonging to these branches is now not available. At present following Śrauta sūtras are available.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;R̥gveda: Āśvalāyana and Śāṅkhāyana. They describe the duties of the Hotr̥ and his assistants.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;White Yajurveda has Kātyāyana-Śrautasūtra which describes the duties of the Adhvaryu and his assistants. This Śrautasūtra is supposed to be belonging to both the recensions of the white Yajurveda viz. Mādhyandina and Kāṇva. The Black Yajurveda has many branches. The Taittirīya-Branch of the Black Yajurveda has six Śrautasūtras. They are as follows: Baudhāyana, Bhāradvāja, Apastamba, Satyāṣāḍha - Hiraṇyakeśin, Vaikhānasa, and Vādhūla. The Maitrāyaṇī branch of the Black Yajurveda has two Śrautasutras, viz. Mānava and Vārāha. Kāthaka-Branch of the Black Yajurveda also had a Śrautasūtra viz. Kāṭhaka srautasutra, but it is available only in the form of a few frag ments.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Among the Śrautasūtra of the Sāmaveda Lātyāyana (Kauthuma-Branch) and Drāhyāyaṇa (Rāmāyanīya-branch) Śrautasūtras are available. They give details of the duties of Udgātr̥ and his assistants.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;4&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Vaitāna Śrautaśutra is a text belonging to the Atharveda. It deals with the ritual duties of Brahman and his assistants.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The Sūtras of Āpastamba, Hiraṇyakeśin and Manava contains details of the Hotř&amp;rsquo;s duties also. These three Śrautasutras and Sūtras of Baudhāyana and Bhāradvāja also mention the duties of the sacrificer. Most of the Śrautasutras contain sections on the duties of the Brahman.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>04 Variety in Taittirīya</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/04_Variety_in_taittirIya/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/04_Variety_in_taittirIya/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(4) The three Śrautasutras of the Taittirīya-Branch of the Black Yajurveda viz. Bhāradvāja, Āpastamba and Satyāṣāḍha Hiraṇyakeśin form one group. Bhāradvāja is sometimes more concise but by and large these three Śrautasūtras very much similar to each other as far as the ritualistic details, style and vocabulary are considered. In comparision to Baudhāyana, they are less diffuse and more concise. They also contain many references to the other schools. Therefore they are more rich than Baudhāyana as far as the contents are considered.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>05 Āpastamba - style and references</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/05_Apastamba_-_style_and_references/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/05_Apastamba_-_style_and_references/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(5) Āpastamba probably belonged to a period later than that of Bhāradvāja. They are very similar to each other in style, structure and order of subjects (except a few details). Sometimes even the wording in both the texts is identical. Āpastamba&amp;rsquo;s rules are at times ampler and somewhat curious.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Āpastamba, like Baudhāyana places Mantras before injunctions. In this respect, he differs from Bhāradvāja.+++(4)+++ Apastamba quotes more authorities than Bhāradvāja.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Āpastamba quotes the views of Āśmarathya and Ālekhana. There are many references to the views of eke (some). Here actually the views of Bhāradvāja are indirectly mentioned.+++(4)+++&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>06 Contents of Āpastambaśrautasūtra</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/06_Contents_of_ApastambashrautasUtra/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/06_Contents_of_ApastambashrautasUtra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(6) Contents of Āpastambaśrautasūtra:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Praśnas 1-4. Darśapūrṇamāsas, Yājamāna&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;5&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Agnyādheya (Establishment of fires)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;5.26-79 Punarādheya (Re-establishment of fires).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;6&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Agnihotra&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;6.16-31. Agnyupasthāna (Praise of Agni).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;7&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Nirūdhapasubandha (Independent Animal sacrifices).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;8&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Cāturmāsya-sacrifices (Four-mounthly-sacrifices).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;8.1-4: Vaiśvadevaparvan.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;8.5-8: Vauṇapraghāsaparvan.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;8.9-19: Sākamedhaparvan.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;8.20-22: Śunāsīrīyaparvan.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;ol start=&#34;9&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prāyaścittis (Expiations).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ol&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;10-13. Agniṣṭoma.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;14.1-12. Ukthya, Ṣodasin, Atirātra, Aptoryāma, Aikādaśīna.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;14.13-15. Cāturhotr̥, Pañcahotr̥, Ṣaḍḍhotr̥, Saptahotr̥,etc.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;15 Pravargya.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;16-17. Agnicayana (Fire-altar-building-rite).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;18.1-7. Vājapeya.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;18.8-22. Rājasūya.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;19.1-10. Sautrāmaṇi (19.5-10 Kaukilī-Sautrāmaṇī)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;19.11-15. Sāvitra, Nāciketa, Cāturhotra, Vaiśvasr̥ja (Agni) (Fire altar-building-rites).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;19.16-17. Kāmya Pasus (optional animal sacrifices).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;19.18-24. Kāmya Iṣṭis (optional Iṣṭis).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;20.1-23. Aśvamedha (Horse-sacrifice).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;20.24-25. Puruṣamedha (Man-sacrifice), Sarvamedha (All-sacrifice).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;21.1-10. Dvadaśāha (Twelve-day-Soma-sacrifice).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;21.15-23. Gavāmayana (YEAR-LONG-sacrificial-session).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;21.24-25. Utsargiṇām ayanam (-sacrificial session).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;22.1-13. Ekāhas (One-day-soma-sacrifices).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;22.14-24. Ahīna-sacrifices.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;22.25-28. Sava (-sacrifices). Sattras (sacrificial sessions).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;24.1-4. Paribhāṣās (General Rules).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;24.5-10. Pravaras (list of important sages in various families).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;24.11-14. Hautraka (the Duties of the Hotr̥-priest).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>07 Prior publications</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/07_Prior_publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/07_Prior_publications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(7) It will be thus seen that Āpastambaśrautasūtra is a model of Taittiriya-manual containing numerous aspects of Vedic ritual although there are some problems regarding the complicated relations between the Sūtras and its basic texts (contrast Gonda, The Ritual Sūtras, I. 521). This text has been critically edited alongwith the commentary of Rudradatta by R Garbe in three volumes (Calcutta, 1882, 1885, and 1902). This edition was re-edited by C. G. Kashikar, (Delhi, 1983 ) along with some correction and emendations to the text. For the present translation Garbe&amp;rsquo;s edition is the basis. Kashikar&amp;rsquo;s corrections and emendations have also been accepted. Apastambaśrauta-sūtra was translated into German by W. Caland (Das Śrautasūtra does Āpastamba I, Göttirgen-Leipzig, 1921, II, Amsterdam 1924, and III, Amsterdam, 1928).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>08 Time and place</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/08_Time_and_place/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/08_Time_and_place/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(8) There is a general agreement among the scholars in connection with the place and time the Āpastambaírautasūtra. It has been accepted by scholars that Āpastamba belonged to the Āndhra-region in the South India. He might have lived not later than the fifth century B.C. His work is one of the comparatively younger works but not one of the youngest works (cf. Garbe vol. III. p. XV-XVI).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>09 Language and style</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/09_Language_and_style/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/09_Language_and_style/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(9) The language and style of the Āpastambaśrautasūtra has a lot of similarity with those of the classical Sanskrit. But still there are some peculiarities and archaisms in the text. Būhler has rightly observed that the ritualists in general were deficient in their education (ZDMG, XL, p. 705). This is correct in later times as well as modern times also.+++(5)+++&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In Āpastamba-srautasūtra the optative third person singular takes yita rather than yeta 16.g. prakṣālayita, abhiprāśayita etc.).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>10 Puroḍāśa</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/10_puroDAsha/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/sUtram/ApastambaH/shrautam/meta/thITe-gaNeshaH/Introduction/10_puroDAsha/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;(10) I draw the attention of the readers to the translation of the following text places from the Āpastamba-srautasūtra in this work:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;VIII.18.5; IX.4.11; IX.14.11; X.5.11-13; X.24.3; XII.5.6; XIII.13.9; XIV.22.13; XVI.35.10; XVII.5.3; XVIII.7.8; XVIII.8.14; XVIII.8.19; XVIII.19.8; XVIII.22.3; XIX. 15.9; XX.25.1; XXI.3.3; XXII.2.23; XXII.14.22; XXIII.7.7.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Everywhere I translate the word Puroḍāśa with the English Expression “bread&amp;quot;. Generally the translators in English German, French use the word “cake” or a corresponding word to “cake”. If we take into consideration the preparation of Puroḍāśa we notice that it is simple-most form of a “bread” rather than of a “cake”. Moreover cake is always sweet. Bread is rather &amp;ldquo;tasteless”, as is Puroḍāśa. Further, in actual practice, the followers of Black Yajurveda roast the flour of rice in an iron pan and then pour water on it. This is similar to the preparation of the South-Indian food-item called “upmā”.+++(5)+++ In the Vedic texts there is no support for this. The followers of white Yajurveda do not do this. They prepare the bread by keeping a ball of flour mixed with water and by convering it with fire. The followers of Black Yajurveda, after preparing a thing similar to upmā, keep it on the potsherds and cover it with fire. The followers of Black Yajurveda belong to South India; that is the reason, perhaps, why their preparation of the sacrificial bread is influenced by the preparation of upmā.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
