<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Yajus incantations for the worship of Rudra from the Kāṭhaka ritual manuals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/2020-12-27_yajus-incantations-for-the-worship-of-rudra-from-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/2020-12-27_yajus-incantations-for-the-worship-of-rudra-from-t/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2020/12/27/yajus-incantations-for-the-worship-of-rudra-from-the-ka%e1%b9%adhaka-ritual-manuals/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This article is available as a &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.files.wordpress.com/2020/12/katha_rudra-3.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf document&lt;/a&gt;. The notes from it are appended below.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The loss of the northern and northwestern Kṛṣnayajurveda traditions due to the Mohammedan depredations of Northern India (aided an abetted by the predatory Anglospheric regimes) has been one the great tragedies faced by Hindudom.+++(4)+++ Hence, it is rather important to collate and restore whatever remains of these traditions, namely those belonging to the Kaṭha and Kapiṣṭhala schools, which were once dominant in the greater Panjab and Kashmir.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on the Bhadra-sūkta, a hymn for felicity to the Vedic pantheon</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/2019-02-10_notes-on-the-bhadra-sukta-a-hymn-for-felicity-to-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/2019-02-10_notes-on-the-bhadra-sukta-a-hymn-for-felicity-to-t/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Source: &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2019/02/10/notes-on-the-bhadra-sukta-a-hymn-for-felicity-to-the-vedic-pantheon/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For better type-setting and Devanagari rendering use &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.files.wordpress.com/2019/02/bhadrasuktam.pdf&#34;&gt;PDF version&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;Several sub-schools of the Taittirīya school of the Kṛṣṇayajurveda possess their own collections of mantra-s distinct from their saṃhitā-s known as the mantra-pāṭha-s. These include mantra-s that are often found in other traditions but not in their own saṃhitā or brāhmaṇa. Additionally, they also include some mantra-s which are unique to these mantra-pāṭha-s. For example the famous Yajurvedic version of the Śrīsūkta is found in the mantra-pāṭha of Bodhāyana. However, most practitioners in South India do not correctly use the accents of this sūkta and seem to be unaware that the KYV version of this sūkta occurs in this text. The mantra-paṭha-s of the Āpastamba, Bodhāyana, Vaikhānasa and Hiraṇyakeśin sub-schools have come down to us. The mantra-s in them are typically deployed in gṛhya rituals directed by instructions from their gṛhyasūtra-s. However, the Vaikhānasa-mantra-pāṭha is distinctive in having a late terminal part that is used in the iconic worship of Viṣṇu by the Vaikhānasa-s. The Hiraṇyakeśī-mantra-pāṭha has a ṛk-saṃhitā as part of it and is used by the Hiraṇyakeśīn-s of Maharashtra and Tamil Nadu in their rituals to this date. In someways this is reminiscent of the hautra-pariśiṣṭha of the Āpastamba-s that is used by Yajurvedin-s to supplement the role normally performed by the Ṛgvedin hotṛ.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Raudra-slant</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/raudra-slant/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/raudra-slant/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The occurrence of “gandharva” in this śloka of the Vāyupurāṇa may not be a textual corruption, in light of this mantra &amp;amp; its brãhmaṇa from the Kaṭhāraṇyakam, which identifies Rudra as the Gandharva-Bhuvanapati.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The lost parts of the kaTha tradition, which was once practiced kashmIra, pA~nchanada &amp;amp; gandhAra also had distinctive rudrian material, e.g., &lt;a href=&#34;https://manasataramgini.wordpress.com/2020/12/27/yajus-incantations-for-the-worship-of-rudra-from-the-ka%E1%B9%ADhaka-ritual-manuals/&#34;&gt;Yajus incantations for the worship of Rudra from the Kāṭhaka&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The above cited brAhmaNa comes just before the famous brAhmaNa section on the arrival of rudra in svarga and the deva-s pacifying him. The frame of this brAhmaNa was later used in the atharvashiras. That kaTha-s used the AV-like rudra (linked in first twt) to their shatarudrIya is suggested by this AraNyaka in the pravargya context: it has a brAhmaNa on the ending of the shatarudrIya combined with the AV-rudra-like  mantra-s: &amp;ldquo;namo rudrAya diviShade yasaya varSham iShavaH&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
