<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;MT on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;MT on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Yajus incantations for the worship of Rudra from the Kāṭhaka ritual manuals</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/2020-12-27_yajus-incantations-for-the-worship-of-rudra-from-t/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/2020-12-27_yajus-incantations-for-the-worship-of-rudra-from-t/</guid>
      <description>Source: here.
This article is available as a pdf document. The notes from it are appended below.
The loss of the northern and northwestern Kṛṣnayajurveda traditions due to the Mohammedan depredations of Northern India (aided an abetted by the predatory Anglospheric regimes) has been one the great tragedies faced by Hindudom.+++(4)+++ Hence, it is rather important to collate and restore whatever remains of these traditions, namely those belonging to the Kaṭha and Kapiṣṭhala schools, which were once dominant in the greater Panjab and Kashmir.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Raudra-slant</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/raudra-slant/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/kAThakam/meta/MT/raudra-slant/</guid>
      <description>The occurrence of “gandharva” in this śloka of the Vāyupurāṇa may not be a textual corruption, in light of this mantra &amp;amp; its brãhmaṇa from the Kaṭhāraṇyakam, which identifies Rudra as the Gandharva-Bhuvanapati.
The lost parts of the kaTha tradition, which was once practiced kashmIra, pA~nchanada &amp;amp; gandhAra also had distinctive rudrian material, e.g., Yajus incantations for the worship of Rudra from the Kāṭhaka
The above cited brAhmaNa comes just before the famous brAhmaNa section on the arrival of rudra in svarga and the deva-s pacifying him.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
