<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;CONTENTS OF TRANSLATION on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;CONTENTS OF TRANSLATION on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/1/</guid>
      <description>1 The new and full moon sacrifices The driving away of the calves The taking of the strew The milking The making of the offering The preparation of the grain The pounding The placing of the potsherds The cooking of the cake The altar The offering of the oblation The sprinkling and the enclosing-sticks The libations of butter The interchange of the ladles The special sacrifices 2 The Soma sacrifice The preparation of the sacrificer The consecration of the sacrificer The place of sacrifice The sacrificial cow The footprints of the cow The measuring of the Soma The buying of the Soma The placing of the Soma on the cart The taking of the Soma to the hall The guest-offering to the Soma The Upasads The high altar The sacrificial carts and the shed The special sacrifices 3 The Victim for Agni and Soma The making of the Sadas The making of the sound-holes The adoration of the altars The adoration of the altars The cutting of the sacrificial post The placing of the post The driving up of the victim The slaying of the victim The cutting out of the omentum The offering of the fat The supplementary offering of the intestines The Vasativari waters The descent of the Soma from the cart The special sacrifices 4 The Soma cups The making ready of the Soma The Upanśu cup The Antaryama cup The cup for Indra and Vayu The cup for Mitra and Varuna The cup for the Aśvins The cup for the Aśvins The Śukra and Manthin cups The Śukra and Manthin cups The Agrayana cup The Agrayana cup The Ukthya cup The Dhruva cup The Seasonal cups The cup for Indra and Agni The cup for the All-gods The cup for the Maruts The cup for the Maruts The cup for the Maruts The cup for Mahendra The cup for Mahendra The cup for the Adityas The cup for Savitr The cup for Savitr The cup for Savitr The cup for the All-gods The cup for Agni with the wives of the gods 28.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/2/</guid>
      <description>1 The special animal sacrifices Offerings for those desiring wealth, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for those desiring freedom from disease, &amp;amp;c. 3. Offerings for those desiring victory, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for those desiring splendour, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for those desiring cattle, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for those desiring villages, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for those desiring splendour, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for those desiring splendour, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for those desiring food, &amp;amp;c. Offerings for certain eventualities Mantras for the special sacrifices 2 The special sacrifices Offerings for those desiring children, &amp;amp;c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/3/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/3/</guid>
      <description>1 The supplement to the Soma sacrifice The Mantras used by the Diksita The Mantras for the placing of the Soma The anointing of the carts and the making of the fire The Mantras for the slaying of the victim The explanation of the Mantras in iii. 1. 4 The stroking of the implements The rivalry of sacrificers The Nigrabhya waters The offerings at the end of the pressings The Pravrtahoma and Vipruddhoma The special sacrifices 2 The supplement to the Soma sacrifice (continued) The Pavamana Stotras The three pressings The gazing on the Soma The Mantras for the creeping to the Sadas The Mantras for the drinking of the Soma The speckled butter The Stotra and the Śastra.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/4/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/4/</guid>
      <description>1 The placing of the fire in the fire-pan. The taking up of the spade The obtaining of the clay The digging up of the clay The taking of the clay The fashioning of the pan The preparing of the pan The Samidheni verses with the offering of five victims 8. The Apri verses for the fire sacrifices The kindling of the fire in the pan The carrying of the fire The Mantras for the offerings at the Vaiśvadeva, 2 The preparation of the ground for the fire The placing of the fire-pan on the throne The adoration of the fire The taking of the fire to the place of piling The piling of the Garhapatya The ploughing of the earth for the Ahavaniya The sowing of the earth The casting of lumps of earth The depositing of the gold plate The depositing of the naturally perforated brick, &amp;amp;c.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/5/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/5/</guid>
      <description>1 The placing of the fire in the fire-pan The libation to Savitr and the taking of the spade The going for the clay The preparation of the ground The gathering of the clay for the altar The depositing of the clay The making of the fire-pan The preparation of the pan The heads of the victims The production of fire in the pan The fire in the pan The Apri hymn for the horse sacrifice 2 The preparation of the ground for the fire The placing of the fire on the throne and its adoration 2.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>6</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/6/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/6/</guid>
      <description>1 The exposition of the Soma sacrifice. The entrance into the hall
The consecration libations
The garment of black antelope skin, the girdle, the horn 4. The obligations of the consecrated
The preliminary offering
The purchase of the Soma
The treatment of the Soma cow
The offerings in the footprints of the cow
The measuring of the Soma
The purchase price of the Soma
The carrying of the Soma in a cart</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>7</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/7/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/CONTENTS_OF_TRANSLATION/7/</guid>
      <description>1 The Ekaha and Ahina Sacrifices The Agnistoma The praise of the Stomas The Atiratra The Dviratra of the Angirases The origin of the Triratra of Garga The Soma cow The giving of the cow The Caturatra of Atri The Caturatra of Jamadagni The Pañcaratra The horse sacrifice (continued), vii. 1. 11-20 The sprinkling of the horse The names of the horse The springing of the horse The first offerings The first offerings The first consecration The Ekavinśini consecration The seasonal consecrations The movements of the horse The Savitras 2 The Ahina sacrifices (continued) The Sadratra</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
