<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>&#43;7 THE EXPLANATION OF THE SOMA SACRIFICE (continued) on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</title>
    <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/</link>
    <description>Recent content in &#43;7 THE EXPLANATION OF THE SOMA SACRIFICE (continued) on यजुर्वेदे विश्वासटिप्पन्यः</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1 The One Day Sacrifices</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/1_The_One_Day_Sacrifices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/1_The_One_Day_Sacrifices/</guid>
      <description>01 Production of offspring is light. Agni is the light of the gods; the Viraj is the light of the metres. The Viraj of speech ends in Agni; it is produced according to the Viraj. Therefore it is called light. Two Stomas bear the morning pressing, like expiration and inspiration; two the midday pressing, like eye and ear; two the third pressing, like speech and support. This sacrifice is commensurate with man, and is perfect [1].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>2 The Ahina Sacrifices (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/2_The_Ahina_Sacrifices_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/2_The_Ahina_Sacrifices_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 The Sadhya gods, desirous of heaven, saw this (rite) of six nights. They grasped it, and sacrificed with it. Then indeed did they go to the world of heaven. Those, who knowing thus perform (the rite) of six nights, go to the world of heaven. (The rite) of six nights is a Sattra of the gods, for these Prsthas are obvious. Those, who knowing thus perform (the rite) of six nights, mount evidently upon the gods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3 The Sattras</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/3_The_Sattras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/3_The_Sattras/</guid>
      <description>01 They go swiftly in that it is the tenth day. In that it is the tenth day they loosen their sins. He who among men going swiftly falls in with a trackless way, he who strikes a post, and he who stumbles, are left out. So he, who on this tenth day, the Avivakya, comes to grief, is left out. If one points out (an error) to one who comes to grief, he seizes hold of him and comes out successfully, and then the one who pointed out (his error) is left out [1].</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>4 The Sattras (continued)</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/4_The_Sattras_continued/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/4_The_Sattras_continued/</guid>
      <description>01 Brhaspati desired, &amp;lsquo;May the gods have faith in me, and may I become their Purohita.&amp;rsquo; He saw this (rite) of twenty-four nights; he grasped it, and sacrificed with it. Then the gods had faith in him, and he became their Purohita. In those who knowing thus perform the twenty four night (rite) men have faith, and they become their Purohitas. There are the three days Jyotis, Go, and Ayus. The Jyotis is this (earth), the Go the atmosphere, and the Ayus yonder (sky) [1]; verily they mount upon these worlds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>5 The Gavam Ayana</title>
      <link>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/5_The_Gavam_Ayana/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://vishvAsa.github.io/vedAH_yajuH/taittirIyam/saMhitA/keith/7_THE_EXPLANATION_OF_THE_SOMA_SACRIFICE_continued/5_The_Gavam_Ayana/</guid>
      <description>01 The cows performed that Sattra, being hornless, with the desire, &amp;lsquo;May horns be born to us.&amp;rsquo; For ten months they performed it, and then horns were born, and they ceased (the rite), (saying), &amp;lsquo;We have obtained (our desire).&amp;rsquo; Then those whose horns were not born ceased (the rite) after making up the year, (saying), &amp;lsquo;We have obtained (our desire).&amp;rsquo; Both those which obtained horns and those which
did not ceased, (saying),&amp;lsquo;We have obtained (our desire).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
